I'm on Instagram where I often take the topic of the most recent podcast episode and expand on it in conversation,
reflections, photos, videos, stories, and more. So if we haven't connected there, I hope you'll find me at Nicole Rokis.
As always, special thanks to Ancestan, should faith radio for hosting and supporting this podcast and so many others.
Until next time, may God teach us to number our days and write that our hearts may be bound with wisdom. Thank you and God bless.
Welcome to the Thursday edition of The Path.
You're connected to The Path, offering strength for our journey towards salvation.
Here's Father Tom Sireka.
Glory to Jesus Christ, glory forever.
Yorlisoningtoangentfaithradio.com.
spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
In our time, many year into break free
of the prison of a flat, secular materialism,
to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and Father Stephen DeYoung,
post this live Colin show,
focused on enchantment and create
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, everyone.
You are listening to the Lord of Spirits podcast as you heard the voice of Steve tell you just several times.
My co-host Father Stephen DeYoung is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana, and I am Father Andrew Stephen Damick in a Mayas, Pennsylvania.
And if you are listening to us live, you can call in at 855 AF radio.
Thank you.
Again, that's 855-237-2346.
And Matyska Trudy, our engineer extraordinaire,
will be taking your calls tonight,
which we will get to in the second part of our show.
So tonight, we are talking about idolatry,
the worship of false gods,
especially as we see it described in the Bible.
Now we've addressed this many times
on the podcast and other contexts,
but tonight we're zeroing in on this question.
Why?
Because in context, it's a me-
part of what the Bible is responding to. And so it's part of how we can understand the gospel and
what Christ's mission to us actually is. So where are we going to start? Well, first we're going to
talk about that pesky question of whether the gods, the pagan's worship really even are a thing.
Ask most modern people, including Christians, whether Zeus, Odin, ISIS, etc., are real, whether
there really is any kind of spiritual being that pagans were
and most are going to say no. These are made up stories to try to explain the existence of things like lightning and earthquakes.
But how did ancient peoples actually see their gods? And more importantly to us Christians, how does the Bible understand these?
And when will we ever discover the true nature of the blood-fued Father Stephen has with James old Jones?
So Father Stephen, is it actually true that all the gods of the nations are demons?
You know, uh...
a lot of people, they've been saying that our last episode,
like they really liked it.
Yeah.
Like some people were saying it was like the best episode
we've done.
Yes, yes.
I think it would be wise when we,
when we start out tonight to let people know
this one's not gonna be as good.
I mean, it would be solid.
Right.
Is it because I jinxed it with the James Earl Jones thing?
No, it'll go right there at the pocket,
but just, you know, there's peaks and valleys, right?
Okay.
There's peaks and valleys.
Some have some looks.
expectations to we can't get into this like
Recursive loop of always trying to one up ourselves like that way lives madness, right?
So you think we should go ahead and do that
Well when when do we go live? Oh, oh we're live now. Oh, that's right. Welcome Lord. Okay. Okay. Yes. Yeah
so
All of the gods of the nations hold doctrines of ministry. Yes
That's what says in the Bible.
Yeah.
clergy joke, that's a clergy joke everybody. And which is a subset of the dad joke. Yeah, yeah,
true. So we're going to start there with where the Bible says that. Right.
Yeah, that's an act like that. But yeah, right, right. The demons. Yeah, so Psalm 96 or 95,
you're looking at the Greek numbering. Verse 5, it simply says, all the gods.
of the nations are demons. That's how it says it if you're looking at a Greek
you know translation from the Greek but when it says in the Hebrew is usually
something like all the gods of the nations are worthless although we're gonna
talk about some other translations of that right so so what's going on there in
the Hebrew and in the Greek? Well if you're if you're if you're reading the Dewey
dreams, you've got the awesome, all the gods of the nations are devils.
That's right. One up again a little bit. But yeah, so it's it's very clear the Greek it's just demons so there's
a word
there in Hebrew
and that word is
roughly Elial and
There's a bunch of things going on with how that word is used not just here
but in a lot of places in the Old Testament words used in the same way
strictly speaking that word means like worthless or you
useless or vain. And it's used in a couple of different contexts. It's used as an adjective,
particularly to describe physicians, shepherds, and oracles.
Which, I mean, okay, so physicians and oracles do tend to be kind of
with in a similar category in the ancient world, but like, shepherds. I mean, they're not, yeah.
I guess it's authority
years maybe. Authorities who are who are kind of worthless, right?
But it's yeah, so it's kind of like quacks, frauds, garbage, you know, yeah.
And so it's used as a noun often to refer to false gods in particular.
So the worthless ones, right. And the reason why that tends to get applied to gods
is that there's a little bit of a pun going on.
with the plural of gods is Ellie and Ellie is close, right?
So your Ellie are Ellie are Ellie.
That's praise money in Hebrew.
Yes, yes.
It flows better off the tongue than it just did for me
if your tongue is more used to Hebrew.
And so this would be used, right?
Wherever we're in a quoted quote polyphistic context,
So this would be used to describe
you know, the other guys, gods.
Yeah.
Your gods are garbage.
So that trash talk before battle was not limited to, you know, your army is no good and
your mother is a hamster, your father sells the Belgerberries.
But also to your gods.
And there's an example of that, probably the best example of that is Sennacherib in the
Old Testament where he shows up and says, you know, don't bother praying to your gods
because all of the other cities we just destroyed, they prayed to their gods too.
And so your gods stink, ours are awesome.
And so just surrender, right?
Yeah, I mean, you see this kind of thing with Pharaoh, right?
With, you know, when the Hebrews come to him and say,
you know, we want to go worship Yahweh
and he's like the God of slaves.
Hello, you know, there is, like this is a,
this is totally a thing in the ancient world
making fun of other people's gods.
Yes, yeah.
So, especially if you're very confident.
in your own. So the thing is, anybody who's listening to this and who has gone and looked
at their local English Bible, that's not the Orthodox study Bible, probably saw it
saying something like all the gods of the nations are idols. Right. And you may be wondering
well, how they get that. Right. Because it's not idols is not literally a translation
either the Hebrew or the Greek.
right right and so the answer is you can't get there directly from the text you have to insert
another presupposition right you have to assume that the idea of the gods being worthless
means that they don't exist right so there's the idea then that they're saying that all the gods
and the nations are idols it's basically saying that the center of their religion is really just this
physical object in front of them that's in their temple or their shrine or whatever.
Right, right. But the problem with that assumption is, for example, that kind of makes
hash of the rest of the ways the word is used. Right? So like, you pay a doctor to
cure something and he fails and you say, you don't exist. Right? You're just a rock.
Yeah. Right? That doesn't make a whole lot of sense. Right? Likewise, you hire a shepherd.
loses all your sheep.
Yeah.
exist. There's a lot of ways to be worthless that in fact most ways to be worthless do not involve
not actually existing. Yes. Yeah. Yeah. It is true that a non-existent physician would be
pretty worthless, but that doesn't mean a worthless physician does not exist by reversing the
syllogism. Yeah. Yeah. And it's so it's fun. It's interesting to look at how this gets translated
and someone actually wrote in and said that
they want more of Father Andrew's etymology
and ancient English corner.
So here it is.
We do theme music.
Yeah, I know.
I know, like, did he have the zither or something
to go back to before this.
Actually, actually it was a parishioner.
It wasn't someone who wrote it now that I remember.
It was a parishioner here in Emmaus, actually.
So yeah.
Right, so I looked this up just to see,
okay, how was this line translated in Old English?
Right. Just as a
a witness to how very early English Christians would have understood this particular word.
And so there is a solter called the Paris solter. And it includes a whole bunch of,
and actually I don't know off the top of my head why it's called the Paris solter, but it has a
bunch of old English in it. But it does, probably because that's where the manuscript was found
or something like that. Because that's where it goes, like another major old English manuscript is
was called the Vertele book, which...
again, that's not an Anglo-Saxon name. But anyway, so the parasolter has translations of,
I think it's most of the Psalms, and the translator rendered them into Anglo-Saxon
alliterative verse, which is great. It re-is very beautifully. So anyways, this particular line
goes like this. For all the gods, the nations, or demons, or are worthless.
This house is an Old English,
Sindon ea la havnu goda hilde deovo,
which basically means sense,
or because all, and uses the word havnu,
which is the, you know, the ancestor of a word heathen,
so all the heathen gods,
and then it uses this word, hilde deovo.
So deovo is the origin of our word devil,
but it seems to be all the gods of the heathen are hill devils.
So there's this notion that you're kind of
of, you know, like Hillbilly demons or, you know, demons that hang around hills or mountains,
that kind of thing. So there you go. Father Andrews, etymology and ancient English corner,
play theme music. Somewhere in Sweden there's a former listener named Hilda Deoful who's
pretty insulted. Yeah, just briefly insulted. Well,
sorry, right? Right in. Let us know your story. So, yeah, Hill Devils,
I'll tell you.
levels. So that's probably the, you know, if we want to talk about a Locust
Classicus of all the gods of the nations or demons, that's it. But there are a
couple of other places that say the same thing. This isn't just one isolated
verse in a psalm, right? Right. So first Corinthians 10, verse 20, St. Paul is
talking about the pagan sacrifices going on in Corinth and why the Corinthian
Christians should stay away from...
them and he says what the nations sacrifice, they sacrifice to demons and not to God.
Right. Right. So he doesn't say they sacrifice to idols or to nothing, nothing,
or to fictional characters, right, but to demons. Right. Yep. Yep. Yeah. And so then there's
another one, Deuteronomy 32 17. This is interesting, if especially if you look at the actual Hebrew
word that's here, which is different from that word worthless.
Elyme. This one says, they sacrificed to demons, not to God, to gods they did not know, to new gods,
new arrivals that your fathers did not fear. So what's the word for demons there in the Hebrew there?
Yeah, so in the Hebrew there, right, it's demons, of course, in the Greek, but the Hebrew has
this word shedding, which we've commented before that Deuteronomy32 is...
is one of the really old and difficult to read parts of the Torah in terms of there's
been no sort of editing or updating of the language at all. And that particular word
is actually a Babylonian loan word it looks like because the word Shedu in Babylonian
refers to a sort of territorial spirit, a spirit that's in charge of an area.
Yeah, the technical term.
English is tutelary spirit tutelary. Yeah, not to be confused with
Tudy from Vax of life.
Good fields.
Has. Wow. Wow. I was I did not see that coming. That was.
Um, so well, you know, with these, with these references, you make, I, I take
the good and the bad. Yeah. Yeah. There you are. That was pretty lame.
But so that was kind of bad. I don't. But I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
So
And we were talking about an area, right, like a territory.
In this case, we're talking about a, like a geographical feature,
right, like a valley, a grove, a cave, a hill, a mountain, not like,
when we hear the word territory, we tend to think of like lines drawn on a map.
So it's not so much of that as
and then place.
range. You know, yeah, plays naturally considered, right? So yeah, so those are those are three sort of
if you want proof texts for the gods of the nations being demons, there's three of them.
But we want to we want to go a little deeper this because where we're heading tonight is
building off of we talked about this a little bit last time sort of in passing as we went.
but how exactly idolatry works and what it is and what
it isn't. And so we have to start out by kind of defining who the beings are who stand behind
the idolatry. Right. Right. Who the gods are who are being worshipped with these idols. So we have
to set the way back machine and rotate back a little bit to some things we talked about way back
in the long and go time at the beginning of the podcast, or so hours ago.
I think that's about true now almost. This is episode 36. We tend to go I
don't know we might not be at a hundred hours yet but we're definitely over 75 or
so yeah yeah yeah so I mean we covered this like in the very first I think it
might be the very first episode actually back before we got you a really good
Internet yeah exactly so probably half of this got lost into the ether as I
I was like, running through my house, trying to reconnect to the internet.
Good times, good times.
Right, particularly.
Last exercise I got, so really.
Okay, so monotheism, right?
Yeah.
That's the word that usually people throw, like Christianity is
monotheists, so that means, of course, these other gods don't
exist. Why do you keep saying these other gods exist apart
from the fact that the Bible says that they exist?
Right, right.
And so as we said, way back in the long ago time, the whole
idea of monothe-
is a bit naff. These categories, well monotheism in particular, I should say, is a term that
comes into being of the 17th century. So we have to keep reminding people of that. It didn't
exist before that, and there's no reason why it shouldn't have existed before that, because it's
based on Greek, monos and thos both existed as Greek words, right?
Right, sure.
But the church fathers for example never called themselves monotheists
They do refer to
The pagans as polytheists but they don't call themselves monotheists ever. This is something interesting
Yeah, yeah in the in the 17th century this term is coined and this is you know
We're revving up to our German friends, right?
This is posted enlightenment
We like to do taxonomy. We like to group things and
categories, right? And then once we've got them grouped into categories, we could
struct our evolutionary flow chart, right? Of which are better, which are worse? And the
modern German ones are always the best ones if you're asking them. But so monotheism gets created
as this category is a way to sort of lump together Judaism and Christianity and Islam.
Yeah, and later on Sikhism and a couple other things right get get thrown in throw
in the side. And then that is over against then polytheism, which is the belief that many gods
exist. Exist and ought and should be worshipped. I mean that that yeah yeah right right right right
right. And then within polytheism there are all of these distinctions that can be made. Right like
there's a henotheism which is kind of the idea that there's lots of gods out there that
that are worthy.
worship but this is the one we worship here. This is our local guy.
And he's the boss. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Right. And he's the boss. But who's the boss can change?
Right. You know if there's a conquest or yeah. And and then that's how you that's how you actually get
then empires that worship fully polytheistically with lots of temples to lots of gods. Essentially it's
It's a kind of conquest game, you know,
so we start to group them together.
Right, right.
And yeah, we have, I think we commented this a little last time,
but we have this idea in our head that there was some kind
of Greek religion that all the Greeks had, or Roman religion
that all the Romans had.
Yeah.
We had this pantheon of gods that was like the Justice League.
And they all had these 12 centuries.
Right.
It was a collection.
And not even collected the same everywhere.
Like, if you lived in a place, like if you think of it more,
like these are my favorite restaurants.
You know, sure, we all have a McDonald's, you know,
but I really love this local burger,
this other burger place.
You know, I don't know,
it's maybe not the best analogy,
but what I'm come up with right now,
and you would go to a particular temple
because the God there was associated with something
that you wanted some kind of success in.
And so you would go, I don't wanna get too far ahead
of ourselves here, but you would go,
essentially like oh you know like you know I like
I feel like Italian tonight or like, hey, I really need to defeat my enemies tonight.
So, so let's go to worship, worship areas, you know, or, or hey, I need a love potion.
I want us to do my neighbor's wife.
So I'm going to go to the, the, the shrine to Aphrodite and offer her, you know, a sacrifice
there, which happens to be one in town, you know.
Even that is very late in Roman, though.
That's, that's sort of a function of what.
Sort of the topical approach.
Yeah.
Well, well, because the Rome, the...
Roman Empire becomes very cosmopolitan.
Right, right.
So I mean, at the Urlair, right,
each Greek city state is worshiping two, three gods.
Right, the ones that are local to them.
They're local gods.
And then as they make treaties and formal alliances,
right, you start getting crossover and that kind of thing.
And then once you get to Rome,
Rome very similar to the United States,
liked to sort of...
tape!
and great value eyes, all the cultures they've encountered.
Right.
Just kind of incorporate, incorporate like a watered down version of whatever.
So we're going to, oh, Egyptian religion, this is interesting.
Let's incorporate a watered down version into Roman religion.
So, yeah.
So once you get to Rome, yes, it's very cosmopolitan.
As St. Paul notices what he's going into Athens, he sees all of the, you know.
Right.
which is interesting.
It's gonna mean the development even in Athens.
I mean, Athens, the name in Greek is Athena,
because Athena is their goddess, traditional.
Right.
Athena and Hephaestus are the originals for Athens.
Everybody else shows up later.
But yeah, so that's an example.
All that we just went through
is an example of the fact that these terms
like polytheism and henotheism
Don't really...
C-
any actual existing religion.
Right, it's the problem with doing these kind of taxonomies
and these categories.
Right, I mean, even just saying monotheism
and that lumping together Judaism, Christianity, and Islam
let alone Sikhism.
Right, like there's a lot more differences there in a lot of ways.
Right, then you're giving credit for.
Right.
Yeah.
And so
Those categories are even less than useful, right, in the first place, right?
Like, they don't serve a very good purpose in the first place.
But then they get kind of turned around and used as cudgles, right?
Like, the whole Muslim apologetic against Christianity is, you guys aren't really monotheists.
And the best response to that, I think, is who cares?
Yeah, like yes, you can construct a category.
monotheism and you can construct it in such a way that it doesn't apply to me. So what?
Right. Like that. Right. That doesn't mean anything in reality. Right. That's just
you constructing a label that pointing out that your label doesn't apply to me. Right.
So I think we've even said in the past that probably the closest word for what you actually see
in the script.
for example, would be what's commanded in the Scriptures, I should say, not what Israel actually
practices, but what is right into the Scriptures. It would be something more like Manoletry.
Right, which literally just means worshiping one. But of course, as you said, it's closest. It
doesn't exactly totally encompass what it is God is telling the people of Israel to do
within the context.
of what they believe about the spiritual world that they live in. Right? Right. Yeah.
Right. Because this isn't an issue of just like Yahweh is Israel's God. And so he wants them to
just worship him and not the other ones, even though the other ones exist. It's an issue of Yahweh,
the God of Israel, is it a completely different category than all the other gods? Right. Thus,
the, I don't know, gazillion times in scripture when it says, you know, who among
the gods is like unto thou, Lord, or like there's so many comparisons like there is.
There is. There is. It's so made. There's none beside me. There's nobody on my level.
Right.
Plenty beneath me, but there's none beside me. Right. And even in the line where it says,
you know, I am, I'm trying to remember where it is, but it says something like I am God.
And before me, there was no other. And after me, there would be no other.
doesn't mean that none existed and none will exist.
means that he's the only God who is truly God in the sense of being, you know, as this
word means in the ancient world, a ruler, the true ruler, right?
The rest are around, but they don't actually qualify to be what it is that Yahweh, the
God of Israel, actually.
They're not in his category, right?
They're in another category beneath him because they're spiritual beings created by him.
Yeah, they're created things.
that before me there was no after me is actually it's
and I say it's attacking the idea of the succession myth.
Yeah, right.
Like, unlike Marduk, Marduk didn't claim
to have always been the most high god.
There's a story about how he became the most high god.
And hypothetically, someone could come afterwards
and overthrow Barduk and become the most high god.
Same thing with Zeus, you know?
Yeah.
So there's the succession.
So that was the God of Israel pointing to yet another
one of those differences between his category and theirs,
which is...
There's no turnover in his category because they know what to do, the turning over.
It's just not a thing. He's God. There's no contest.
You see reflected both in Scripture and outside of Scripture within paganism,
This idea that the spiritual world is teared.
right, that not all divine beings or spirits or gods and scripture uses all those terms.
They're not all on the same level, even if you're a pagan, right?
Yeah.
So it's not that the pagans were like super egalitarian about the spiritual world and Jews were just
super hierarchical.
Yeah, yeah, there's even you know even even before you get these
worked out pantheons with a sort of a clearer hierarchy.
There's still, almost everybody has a sense of,
okay, there are sort of big gods and little gods.
There's the God that we worship at the temple
in the center of town, and then there's the God
that's out at the tree that I go to once in awhile.
And they're understood to be on different levels.
And you eventually get the sense that they're
the way that it's described as if they're sort of related.
Like this lesser one is a son of the greater one or a daughter.
You know, right.
So they know the difference between Poseidon and a Nihat, right?
And they know, right, oh, there's a spirit of this river.
And it's, well, they would say it's related in a way to Poseidon, right?
Who's out there, the ocean, right, to see.
But they, they, they're not on a plane.
And that gene.
ideology element is what is typically used in all of these pagan stories in order to
can note this idea of tears and relations. We tend to take it very woody literally, right?
And it's not that those pagan gods weren't running around fornicating. They are in all the stories
at least. But it wasn't primarily about constructing a family tree. It was about the
idea of conveying hierarchy, of conveying, you know, this, this tear level, because of course
the son or a daughter is less than in the ancient world their father or mother because they're
derived from them. Right. Right. Yeah. I mean, that's just a huge piece of what the culture is like,
which is, you know, which is the basis for when, when, when Jesus quotes Psalm 110, right, where he says,
the Lord said to my Lord, how could David call?
him Lord if he is his son because everyone understands that sons are not the lords of their fathers.
It always goes the other way. But of course in Christ's case, he is the Lord of his father
David because he's God. Right. Right. And you can see this in the pagan settings. You know,
Aries God of War has kids like Aris who's strife, you know, strife is sort of low level, right?
that Phobos is fear.
Right, it's sort of all, right?
And so you can see how this works in that sense, right?
So it's not so much like, no, no, we've researched this, you know, lineage of demonic powers,
but that it's this idea of derivation and subsidiarity, right?
To the more sort of powerful spirit.
So that kind of...
of gets in different cultures, that idea of tears or categories or types or qualities
of these gods and divine beings sort of plays out in different ways, right? We're given
one model basically by the scriptures and by the Israelite and Second Temple Jewish tradition.
And then we're going to go through that in a second.
And once we do them and you...
compare that to the pagan schema. We'll see there's continuities and discontinuities, but
that the core ideas are there and as we've seen over and over again are sort of being corrected
by the biblical model by the prophets.
Right. And this feeds into one of the main themes of this podcast which is that ancient
people are largely all describing the same experience of the
spiritual world, but they have different takes on it. Right? They have different ways of
interpreting and understanding and telling the stories about it. And a lot of, as you said,
a lot of what the Bible is doing is saying, no, no, this is the truth. Right? And because of
our Christians, we believe what the Bible says about these spiritual beings and not the stories
that are being told within paganism. Right. That that's the correct story. Right? The story that's
the way to understand.
the spiritual world correctly.
And so this is again a little bit of review I think,
but it's from some early episodes.
So it's worth doing again,
as much as we tell people to go back and listen in order,
that it's getting mean at this point.
It's worth it binge it people.
Sorry, you got kickbacks or something?
No.
Bad way.
John, right?
It's an idea.
So I...
In sort of the hero bottles we've talked about before.
So you've got these, if we accept the devil himself, right?
And various devil figures we've talked about before.
You've got basically three categories of what could be called demons.
Okay.
All right. So yeah, number one is.
the one that everybody always gets the most excited about. Watchers.
Yeah. Yeah.
Well, I don't know. We're going to get to giants. People get excited when we talk about
it. It's true, but they're related. Yeah. They're related.
The more layers than one. Yeah. Indeed. Indeed. Right. Yeah. The watchers.
So this is the biblical model. The watchers are these these spirits that get
imprisoned in the abyss. Right. So this is watchers is the term that's used in
first DNA in the book of DNA.
it's also used in Daniel. And these are the angelic beings who get involved with Canes line
to teach them, you know, things like metallurgy, teach them secrets, right? Secret knowledge that they
don't have that they intend for them to use to destroy themselves. Right. And so those rebellious angels
according to St. Jude's epistle.
second Peter very clearly are imprisoned in the Abyss or Tardarus if we're talking about
second Peter Tardarus will show up again in a minute but those are the the Abyss is more of the
ancient Near Eastern language where like the upcalo and the Babylonian version of this story are
imprisoned. But so they're imprisoned there awaiting sort of the day of judgment.
Then you've got
But that relationship that they have with Canes line and then going forward after the flood produces the Nephilim, produces the Giants.
Yes, which are also called unclean spirits.
Well, let's say die, yes.
Yeah, after that, yeah, exactly, after they die.
And the reason that they're called unclean spirits is,
if you look closely at especially Leviticus,
then you'll see that
things that are mixed together that ought not be, which is a whole category, you know,
a whole bunch of different stuff, right? But things that are mixed together are touching
together that should not be kind of unholy hybrids are regarded as unclean. And the idea
with these dead giants, these dead Nephilim, is that they are in some way a mixing together
of the Watchers and Humanity and
No, we're not saying it's a genetic DNA mixing. No, we're not saying that the watchers have physical bodies that they can biologically reproduce with. Go back in the listen to the Giants episode.
But nonetheless, they are called unclean spirits because there is in some way this sort of mixing, this hybridization going on between these evil spirits and human beings.
And then these are the dead, disembodied souls.
of these beings. So these are humans, right? The unclean spirits are human spirits?
Yeah, well, dead demonized humans. Yeah. Yes, right. Not just any human spirits there.
Right? That unclean mixture, like one of those new Reese's peanut butter cups with a potato chip.
Like why would you do that? Is that really a thing? Yes. I recently got the white
I talked at ones and I thought they were rather good and not too far off, but the Tata chip.
That's that ain't right.
Potato chip.
Yeah.
Some of the density scrolls actually called the spirits of illegitimate birth.
I don't think I could say the other word.
Oh, wow.
For that on the potato chip thing.
But yeah.
That heads for it.
No.
Right.
And so that you got water in my humanity.
You got humanity in my watch.
Sorry.
As we as we said before, the go to place on that.
These are the demons.
who we see being cast out in the synoptic gospels, for example, in the book of Acts.
And it go to place on that, it's the guy's doctoral dissertation is the origin of evil spirits
by Archie Wright, not Kerry Grant, but Archie Wright.
And you can read all, he has all the sources that that's just what people
in the first century BC in the first century BC.
A.D. thought demons were right. It's pretty
conclusive on that level. So that's
another cat. Now most of those are also
in prison in the abyss but there are
some that are still sort of roaming
around the world. Right. Yeah.
Which if you read Jubilee's you get
that story right? How 90% get tossed.
Yeah. With massive 90% get tossed in
the abyss. 10% are allowed to roam the
the world, uh, afflicting the wicked.
and God lets them do it basically to bring the wicked to repentance.
Right. That includes us.
Right. And that idea is what St. Paul's talking about when he talks about
excommunicating someone and handing them over to St.
for their destruction of their body and the salvation of their soul is he's
saluting to that idea, that concept of why the demons are out there.
And so these are these unclean spirits are bodyless.
And these are the ones who are going,
as we just mentioned, to go around possessing people.
Both in the context of the demonic possessions
we see in scripture and also the context of like oracles
among the nations.
And they also are going to then go into constructed bodies
because we're head towards idolatry here.
Yes.
Yep, yep.
So then, yeah, go ahead.
The third category in the biblical model are the gods of the nation's proper, right?
So like the gods of Egypt to get judged at the Passover, right?
Or the gods of the Romans, the gods of the Babylonians, the, you know, pick your, pick your nation.
These are the angelic beings from the Tower of Babel's story who are placed over the nation's.
the princess.
who Daniel talks about the Prince of Persia, the Prince of Greece, the powers of
principalities that St. Paul talks about, which he talks about being in the heavenly places,
the angels who gather on the left in the Divine Council according to St. Gregory the Great in the
this century in his Baralea. These are those gods.
So they're angels that God had put over the nations who fell by accepting worship for themselves.
Right. Right. Yeah. And so you may have noticed
right there with those last two groups that if you have
one of the demons in that unclean spirit category in an idol, but that idol is of one of these
God's of the nations.
that they're working in sort of working in tandem,
right, like they're working together.
And you find exactly this in second-time Jewish sources.
Right. So there's this idea that a pagan
might be bowing down to a statue of Zeus,
and yet it's some dead Nephilim jumping in there
and actually engaging with the pagan.
Right. Right.
And the place where this comes up usually.
in second-templed Jewish writings, even in some early Christian writings, is they're
talking about, I was going to say, hero worship, but technically in the Greek and Roman
context, that's a different thing.
Because there literally was hero worship.
Right.
But, you know, someone goes and leaves an offering before a statue of some general who just
died in a war.
Right.
Thank you.
And so the question arose, well, wait, like is that really idolatry?
Because we know that's that's just some guy who just died.
And it's just sort of a nice gesture, right?
Or various forms of things that we would call like ancestor worship, right?
And, you know, dad, grandpa, great grandpa, was it necessarily a nephilim?
Hopefully, right? But what you find in those second-temple Jewish and early
Christian sources is that when those kind of things happen,
their sword.
of a demon ready, one of the unclean spirits ready to sort of swoop in and get in between,
right?
Right.
Intercept.
And then we don't have to necessarily believe the story that the pagan is telling about
what's happening because, you know, demons are liars and happy to deceive them.
Right.
And so, yeah, any chance they get, they're happy to dart in there and take advantage of it.
So those three categories in broad strokes just to you
the Greek traditions as an example, right?
The pagan Greek traditions,
because they're more familiar to most people.
You find those same categories.
Yeah, so this is interesting.
This is one of these places,
like we keep talking about to say that people in the ancient world
are largely all talking about the same things
just kind of in different ways.
And often one of the ways that you see this playing out
is they are all having experiences
of these kind of categories of spirits.
Ruff.
They have different stories about, you know, how they got to be what they are and all that kind of stuff and how you should interact with them.
But it's still basically the same kind of categories.
But those stories connect and interact with each other also.
Yeah, right.
They're living in the same physical world and the same spiritual world.
Right.
And so they're these intersections.
Alright, so for example in the Greek stories you have
Titans and Prometheus, right, who are these sort of ancient class of gods.
Prometheus is a special good example, but there's a few other Titans who do similar things.
And face the similar fate, they give knowledge to man that man is not supposed to have, right?
And they are punished by being imprisoned in Tartarus, right, which is just a directly parallel
and pretty much exactly the same story as what the Bible says about the watchers.
You know, like Prometheus, for those of you, maybe it's a long time since you read Greek mythology.
Prometheus is the one who gives fire to human beings and then he gets...
Because of the liver pecked out by a vulture.
Yes, I think every day because it grows back.
Yes.
Yes, lovely.
Because he's changed his side of Iraq.
Yeah, never let it be said that the Greek gods aren't creative in their punishments.
But yeah, so it President Tartarus and this isn't just
Father Steven and father Andrew now saying hey look at these two ancient stories aren't they kind of similar as I mentioned before St. Peter
Talks about the angels who sinned in the type of Noah and got imprisoned in Tardarus. Yeah, that's literally the word he uses is Tardarus
He pulls these two stories together. He connects them
Right, this isn't this isn't some new model thing this happens in the New Testament
So we have that category.
They have obviously they believe in spirits that inhabit idols. They do the ritual right for that to happen.
They have oracles oracle at Delphi being the most famous one or they believe is possessed by Apollo. Right.
They have phenomena of demon possession, you know Socrates says he's possessed of a demon. Kings and stuff have a
a deeminar genius once we get to the Roman period.
And so this is a phenomena that makes me it's as well these spirits are sort of a different category of spirits
Right then the Titans for example, right and then the third category for them would be manifested mostly by the Olympians and then later by all the other gods
Right who they come up worship you know who are the powers and principalities the ones who are ruling over them now
Yeah, that's it's Zeus and Hera and Athena and Apollo and you know
all those guys. Yeah, if you go back to those older episodes, we quote from Plato, where Plato
literally tells the story about them having been a lot in certain territories, just like in the
Babel story, right, from which they were going to rule over those areas. And Athens got
Festus and Athena, that's theirs, right? And Plato talks about how at first they ruled as sort of
gentle shepherds and then something happened.
It's a sort of indeterminate point and the sort of golden age of that ended.
But so there's this same kind of structure.
And then within that structure, you get sort of the Greek version of Chacanto Machi.
Right.
Which again, everybody, that's a wonderful term that means war against giants.
War with giants, yeah.
several things here, we're going to talk about a little more that we've brushed into here and there.
But so the way this happens is in the Greek story, there's sort of this
catholic Gaia, right? So Gaia is the earth. Earth and
catholic is the underworld slash Hades. Yeah.
We've talked about how in Hebrew, Aritz can mean the earth or the land, it can also mean the underworld.
The same is true with Gaia.
of an eccothonic version of her, right?
Because, you know, it's not just the earth,
but all the holes and pits and caves and, right, caverns.
And so she's angry because the Titans were her kids.
Right, which the Olympians threw them into Tardarus.
Right, yeah.
And so to get revenge, she first brings forth the giants.
right? And so there's this war against the giants.
And I should point out here, everybody, if you actually look at the Greek
mythological sources that talk about these giants, they do not make the
consistent or even persistent claim that they are physically tall. The
thing that really seems to make be how they're actually described as that
they're really fierce and aggressive and really tough, tough warriors.
is their deal, not that they're super big. Right. So just a note. And as another note, the
high altar of Pergamon, which was an altar, a victory, altar to Zeus, that in his letter to the
church of Pergamon in Revelation, Saint John refers to as the throne of Saintin, which is now in a
Berlin Museum.
Brits didn't get that one in time.
Has this gigantomaki? That's what's depicted.
Yes, right.
On the side of it.
Yeah, I mean, you can Google it up people and see
or use your favorite search engine,
altavista maybe.
And you can see pictures of pictures of it
on the marbles and stuff that are associated with that.
Use Publish or Clearing Houses.
Search engine you get free sweepstakes entries every time you search
Is there anybody out there who still uses archie and go for please write in I'd love to hear from you ancient ancient people
So
Deep deep after after the gigantobaki does it sort of doesn't work
She brings forth typhon who's the great beast who comes up out of the sea
I feel like I've heard that somewhere before but more on that later. What beast out of the sea?
Yeah.
And Typhon is described as being this kind of weird,
hodgepodge of other creatures.
And he's sort of the ultimate expression of the wrath of the Titans.
Anyway.
And so,
the, the, that beast is sort of defeated by the Olympians,
which is sort of their ultimate establishment of order.
He's this chaos monster out of the sea.
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean, like in He's
Typhon is the son of Gaia and Targerus. Like, wow, what a what an unholy union that is. Yeah.
That's worst. The underworld and hell got together and brought you this.
But this Typhon imagery as we alluded to is what is getting picked up by Daniel and Revelation.
Right. And what's happening there
is that they're taking that story and inverting it, right?
Because from the perspective of the Greeks and the Romans, right,
the Olympians are the good guys, and the Olympians are basically them.
Right, right.
And so, no, they are in their minds.
We Romans, right, we Greeks represent the triumph of order over chaos.
Right, I mean, yeah.
Yeah, that was it.
And you see the exact same thing in Norse mythology, right?
So Odin, the all father.
But I mean, he wasn't always the all father.
Once again, he defeats this great primeval giant
emir with his brothers, Villion Bay.
And as I think I've mentioned in this podcast before,
when they stab him in the toe, a flood of blood comes out
and largely drowns all the giants in the world.
So there's like, there's this, again, there's
Chegantomaki, there's the destruction of...
of monsters to set up these gods as being the ones who are really in charge and are the
good guys.
You know, I mean, it's the same really, it's the same story over and over again, just with
a little bit of different details.
Right, right.
But so what Daniel is saying through his vision and its interpretation, what's a John is
saying through his vision and its interpretation is, no you guys are the monster.
Are we the baddies?
Yeah.
You guys think you're the ones establishing order and justice, but you're the monsters. You're chaos. You're destruction
You're worshipping it. You're following after you represent it in the world
Right, and you're gonna be defeated and you're gonna be judged by the actual God
Hmm who created the universe and will bring will bring justice to the universe
Unless you do something real quick, right?
Right. Right. Right. And you even see in Revelation.
And again, you know, this would be multiple episodes at some point to go through any of the
stuff in Revelation. But it's worth comparing the Harlet and the Beast to Gaia and Typhon
and the relationship there.
That's, wow, that's fun. All right. Well, after that little cataloging of demons and such from
from the ancient world, we're gonna take a short break and we'll be
right back.
Christ's defeat of demons, sin, and death, written by Andrew Stephen Damick.
This book is not a sales pitch.
I hope that instead it will be an authentic, true proclamation of the gospel.
How or whether you respond to it is important, but I'm not going to make a marketing appeal
to you at the end.
Knowing what the gospel is and being able to teach it to someone else does not require
that you know everything in this book.
Bye bye.
By the end of it, you should know what a gospel is, why there is a gospel at all, what
the gospel is, and what the response to it requires.
Arise, O God, the gospel of Christ's defeat of demons, sin and death.
Now available as an audiobook at audible.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Steven DeYoung. If you have a question, call now at 8.
5, 5, 2, 3, 7, 2, 3, 4, 6.
That's 8, 5, 5, A, F, Radio.
Welcome to the second half of the podcast.
We're talking idolatry, we're talking demons,
gods, all that awful stuff.
Before we get into the next part
of what we're gonna be discussing,
we actually have a couple of callers that we wanna talk to.
And the first one is Matt.
So Matt, are you there on the line?
I am. Can you hear me? I can hear you welcome Matt the Lord of Spirits podcast. What is on your mind?
Okay, so sacrifice has been discussed quite a bit on the show and the nature of it and one of the
main messages is that sacrifice is that it's core like a meal that you share with your God
and it's like a hospitality thing to improve relations.
And so with that understanding,
is it sinful at this point in history,
a post-crisifixion resurrection
with the presence of the Eucharist
for a Christian to still sacrifice food to Yahweh?
So, you know, you put it just ambiguously enough
at the end there that it's like,
well, it depends on what you mean, right?
So an-
And we'll talk about why that's true.
So, I mean, the Eucharist is a sacrifice of food to Yahweh,
right?
Because it's bread and wine that we're sharing with God.
So, and this is commanded by Christ, right?
When he said, do this as my remembrance, right?
But I think maybe underneath your question
is sort of the issue of, is it okay to sacrifice other foods?
like, you know.
barbeque, which if you're if you're where I'm from, that is pulled pork with basically vinegar on it.
So, yeah, you know, or whatever else it might be.
And there's a good answer to that.
And I'm going to I think I know what he's going to say, but I'm going to punt it over to Father Stephen
to hear what he has to say about that.
So the key is that
The Torah makes clear you're not allowed to sacrifice whatever you want, whenever you want,
wherever you want.
Right?
What does?
Okay.
So it's not just a question of hospitality, but it's, it's, I mean, we're talking about
hospitality and overarching category in the ancient world, right?
And so obviously different cultures had different rules for sacrifice, like they could sacrifice
people, right?
the Torah was very strict about that.
right? You read the instructions and it's, you know, this many of this type of animal
on this day in this one place, you know, by this officiant, right? You know, or the Passover,
one lamb per household, unless your household's small, then you could share with another
small household, etc. But there's very strict rules. And that's a general thing about
worship all the way through the Torah and sacrifice obviously is the central
act of worship, right?
Nate Abbott, Abihoo decided to innovate with their offering of incense and it did go so well for them.
So I think the same broad principle would apply today, right?
That when Christ says, as Father Andrew said, do this as my remembrance, right?
We have this tradition of worship we've received.
Try to sort of riff off of that.
or innovate from that,
would be a bad thing.
Yeah. Yeah.
The other thing I would add, by the way,
and this was one of the things that I learned,
which was really fascinating to me.
If you listen to our episode that we did about Abraham,
I think we titled it from Er of the Caldees or something like that.
There, we talk about the incident
where Abraham is called by God to offer up eyes.
on the mountain. And before he can do that, of course, God stops him and a ram is given as the sacrifice
instead. And one of the things that Father Stephen pointed out was that this was interpreted by
second-tempor Judaism and by, well, not by second-tempor Judaism so much, maybe, I don't know,
They've correct me in this, but it's certainly by the early church as an indication that animal sacrifice.
was being provided by God until such time as the one who is sort of the true and final
Isaac that is to say Christ comes and is sacrificed. So it would be it would be a kind of
adjudiizing thing. You know, in other words, acting like the Messiah has not come, if we
were to offer up, you know, other kinds of things on the altar other than what he has commanded
us within the new covenant. Did I get that right, Father Stephen?
about
Yeah, because there was an early connection of the Messiah to Isaac, particularly in terms
of the suffering servant in Isaiah, that led to that broader interpretation, that the sacrificial
rituals of the old covenant were sort of for that purpose, for that time, right?
Yeah.
And that Christ is the final fulfillment of all of that.
And so therefore, I mean he's off, he's given us himself to offer on his
Why would you offer something else?
Yeah.
You know, and there's even like cannons against things like offering milk and honey, which you know if someone makes a rule against it, that means that someone was doing that.
So, you know, they're there, they're even comments saying, you know, don't do this other thing.
As well. So does that make sense Matt?
Yeah, I'm curious, do you recall where those cannons are?
It's in one of the ecumenical councils, but I can't remember off the top of my head.
Yeah.
Yeah, very good answer. Thank you very much.
All right. Well, thank you very much for calling Matt.
Okay. We've got Bill calling.
Bill, are you there?
I am here. Can you hear me, fathers?
We can hear you, Bill. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Thank you very much. It's good to be here.
So what's up?
My question has to do with what's modern penicostles called Glossolalia.
And if that has any relation to like the ancient gods of the nations.
So
A bit of backstory, I was raised in a costal, I was taught that glossary,
it was kind of the Holy Spirit speaking through you.
And I was deeply disturbed when I found out that other religion had the same
manifestation as well.
I understand and get that reference in Greco-Roman religious literature,
modern African and Indian, sorry, Indonesian religion.
Maybe Indian, I don't actually know.
Mormonism, I do know though, and I don't know what to make of this phenomenon.
So the question is there on I-
or practice in the ancient world of virtual babbling or speaking a divine language
as a kind of worshiping or secret knowledge or communion with our God.
And if so, what's going on there?
Yeah.
Well, I mean, the short answer is yes.
You know, ecstatic utterances definitely go with ancient paganism.
So I actually want to come and I thought this is a really interesting subject for me.
I so not to sell my book too much, but I wrote a book called Orthodoxy and
Header Doxie and there's a whole chapter on Pentecostalism. And one of the things
that I discovered as I was researching it, because I didn't know this until I
started researching it, is that the first Pentecostals, you know, late 19th century,
actually their understanding of the gift of tongues was like what you actually see
at Pentecost in the book of Acts, which is to say they were being given the
RACUS Ability
to speak foreign languages, right?
Or, I mean, you could also interpret what happens in acts as being like the Star Trek
universal translator, you know, the Apostle speak and everyone simply hears his own language,
which is the language is actually used there in acts.
But in any event, like early panic oscillals, like they said they were speaking Swedish or
Chinese.
Those are actual examples.
And so they, this is related.
I'll get to why.
So they sent out missionaries all over the world.
Ready to...
because they believed they were given this gift to do this one final great evangelism before the end of the world was going to come.
And so they sent out missionaries, but of course it didn't take long for the missionaries to realize,
hey, wait a minute, I'm not actually speaking Swedish or Chinese,
where if I am, these people don't seem to understand me.
And they came back and within the space of a decade,
the theology of what speaking in tongues was shifted within Pentecostalism from being that,
which generally is called Xenoglossia.
which is the gift of foreign languages to Glossololia,
this sort of ecstatic utterance, right?
So the reason why this is relevant to what you asked
is because you asked like what's going on there
and people often ask like is there something demonic
in Pentecostal tongue speaking, right?
Is that one of the questions maybe on your mind?
Yeah.
So here's my take on it.
And this is my take. This is not the ruling of an ecumenical council or even what I was taught in seminary.
I don't even remember it being addressed when I was in seminary.
My take is this is that there's a number of possibilities.
One is that it's a purely psychological phenomenon.
People can enter into states of altered consciousness and begin to speak
ecstatic utterances like this is a thing and you can actually even track it
scientifically right within paracol
you know, instruments and they can actually see that the brain starts working in a different way. Right.
So I think that that's one possibility.
Another possibility is and some and I'm not saying that it could it's one of these. It could be any or all of them, depending on who and where and when you're talking about. Right.
Another possibility is is utter fraud. Just totally fraud people making it up.
Another possibility is that it's...
It's people that are honestly deceived,
and maybe they're deceived by having
the psychological experience
and maybe they're deceived by actually interacting
with demonic beings.
So I think that all of those are possibilities.
One of the things that tells me that it's not
proper orthodox Christians,
aside from the fact that you simply don't really see it
in orthodox Christianity,
although I've heard about some possibilities.
certain corners of church history. But is that in many cases within Pentecostal tongue speaking,
you've got people teaching other people how to practice it. I don't know if you had that
experience as a Pentecostal yourself. Like just make some sounds, and you'll eventually, it'll kind of
unleashed. They tried it didn't really happen. Yeah, yeah. Right. And sometimes I'll try to
to instigate it in other people, like make them...
start. And then the other thing, and this is what
thing that's interesting for me is a kind of amateur, you know,
linguist. And I emphasize the word amateur is I've noticed that
tongue speakers seem to use largely speaking the phonemes that
is to say the sounds of language like the vowels and the
consonants together, right? The phonemes that are native to
the language that they already speak. So largely tongue
speakers on.
not making sounds that are foreign to them. Which if you've ever tried to learn
another language, you know that usually that other language has sounds that
you're not used to making, right? Like my favorite is the Arabic vowel,
AIN. There is nothing in English like that vowel and it's one that trips up a
lot of people, you know, and I'm sure I just said it wrong, right? But I've noticed
that tongue speakers tend to speak in tongues with the phonemes they already know
which suggests to me that there is at least a strong psychological element to
what's going on there.
I don't know as much about this from the ancient world. I do know that glossololia does exist in pagan religions
and so I don't know Father Stephen if you know about that in a way that I don't. It's just something I know that it existed
and sometimes was associated with oracles and stuff.
Yeah, I got to um actually you a little bit because-
Okay, go for it.
You kind of just went full materialist, do you realize that?
Did I?
Like if they hook you up to a brain meter and detect something that means there's nothing spiritual about it?
No, that's not what I meant.
Okay, that's not what I meant. No, no, no, no, no, no, I'm saying that it is something that can be observed
Right, there is there are things to observe. Yeah, when you when you hook people up. Yeah, yeah, yeah
Just say it is all no
Thank you for the opportunity to clarify. Yeah, so
I don't have a reputation for being nice. I think most of the time
there's a demonic
element to it, but that takes different forms. That doesn't mean I think people are 99%
of the time demonic, demonically possessed.
Right. That's like pedicostles are all demonically possessed, right? Because there's other ways
demons can be involved, right, in temptation and in other things, right, aside from just
straight up possessing people. And I think the really dangerous part, as you know, this
the ecstatic experience, the production of the ecstatic.
experience by techniques is a commonplace in ancient magic and ritual. Yep. And
ecstatic utterances are one of the earmarks of that, right? And so anything that
puts you into an altered state of consciousness it doesn't have to be psychedelics
for example, right?
Oh, what the heck? I could say whatever I want.
I guess. Wow, here we go. People who have spent time at evangelicalism know, for example,
that if you keep people on their feet for a certain amount of time and you have them
saying repetitive prayer courses, praise courses of a certain length, you could produce
an ecstatic experience. Everyone will walk out of their swearing. They felt the Holy Spirit.
Right. And the people who organize those things know that. I mean, I used to be, you know,
I used to do big concerts and that kind of thing and that kind of technique is
absolutely involved in the kinds of experiences that people have, you know, at rock concerts
at plays at whatever.
Right.
And you can have them at sporting events, right?
You can have them at, but, but again, regardless of how you engineer it, whether it's with pharmaceuticals
or whether it's through those kind of techniques, you're putting someone into an altered state of
consciousness, which thereby makes them spiritually vulnerable.
the vulnerable, the spiritual deception. It makes them...
vulnerable in various ways. There's also the whole issue and this is really what
we're going to be talking about for most of the rest of the show. Anything
spiritual in which you are told to apply a technique, you should run from like
fire. Right. That's where you're told here's this technique, follow this
technique and it will produce this results, that's not Christianity. Right?
That is another kind of religious experience.
So the reason I said 99% right,
is that there's always this 1% of weird things.
Like if you've read enough of the Bible,
you know there's these weird things.
Like where Saul goes to the city of prophets
and rips off all his clothes
and flops around on the ground prophesying right
or a zikiel running around naked or right.
So there's these...
So I'm not going to say that there hasn't been some case in the history of the church,
where a Christian received a vision from God, and that was accompanied by some kind of
ecstatic utterance. That's why I have to leave that 1% open. But even if we accept that
that happened in that 1.01% or whatever it is of cases, that's the fringe in the extreme
fringe in the extreme, not the norm. Right?
Like we don't read about that happening to Saul and so we say hey when I go to church when I go to liturgy this week
I'm gonna strip off all my clothes and roll around on the floor, right? Please don't
You know, we don't do that because we accept well this is this weird kind of extreme thing right and
That alone right that alone. I think is enough to say to the Pentecostal practice
right where they've taken that which would be
at best.
this kind of extreme or fringe or rare spiritual, exceptional spiritual currents and trying
to make it the norm. Some of them even teach if you haven't done it, you're not saved.
Right. Where I mean, that's as norm as you can get. They're taking something out at the
fringe, I jot at the pizzo and moving it to the center, right? And you're not going
to have a good time when you do that. So yeah, that's what I have to say about that it's
dangerous for that.
reason and is not something to be pursued. There are plenty of things that we have to pursue in our
Christian life and work toward. And I don't see how that could take precedence over the giving of
alms, prayer, fasting, worship, you know, prayer with our families, right? Pursuing a kind of
So, the esoteric experience seems to be...
be a waste of time better spent elsewhere repeating at all.
Yeah.
That makes sense to you, Bill.
It does.
If I might ask real quickly, my priest is also a former penicostle who did this before
and now thinks that it was more of a hypnotic experience which just seemed, it might be true,
but it just seems too much of a materialist explanation.
I've been really looking for an orthodox.
understanding of this that doesn't slain too heavily into pure materialism. So,
the good resource and the cypher morphoxine heterodoxy, which I know obviously have to check out,
that goes over the spiritual understanding of this, both contemporary, but also like in ancient
religions and the ancient world, priority on the first but the second fault is really interesting.
I'm not aware of any book that does what you're describing.
the only other text that I'm aware of that deals with tongue-speaking and penicostalism in general
in any kind of focused way. Now maybe there's a scholarly thing I haven't read, I don't know, but
is so Father Stair from Rose has a book called Orthodoxy in the Religion of the Future, which came out
in the 1970s, or at least that's when he wrote it. And he very, very, very much all out says, you know,
So this is a demonic
experience, it's demonic possession. So he gives a very, I regard as a kind of extreme
reading. You know, like I would agree with Father Steven that I don't think it's a matter
of being possessed by like a devil, you know, necessarily, right? I mean, maybe in some
cases that is what's going on. But but Father Sarah from takes a very, very strong tack against
it. But at the time also, you know, frankly, the movement was quite different in his period
than it is now.
It's really mainstreamed in a lot of ways.
You know, so yeah, I don't know father. Do you know of anything that really deals with this and like Mike Bill is describing?
Yeah, I mean not not off the top of my head.
If I if I find something good, I'll pass it along to father Andrew and he could post it.
Yeah, somewhere on the hitter webs.
Yeah, so on his tweet talks or whatever.
I quit Twitter. I'm a Twitter Twitter.
So...
All right. Well, I hope that that's helpful to you, Bill. Thank you very much for calling this evening.
All right. Well, rolling right along, now we're going to talk about
idolatry and how it actually works. Like what is, what exactly is going on with idolatry?
And to start with that, we're going to talk about things that are not actually idolatry,
but get called it, right, Father? Right. Yeah. Idols. How do they work? And, uh,
And yeah, first we have to do some ground clearing.
because we have a bunch of ideas in our heads.
We briefly mentioned this last time,
but we have these ideas in our head.
A lot of them come from, frankly,
as we're gonna see, a lot of them come from other discussions.
They come from, for example,
intra-pronistent issues,
where people are wanting to categorize things as idolatry,
so that they could them,
condemn them as idolatry.
even if they're not sort of idolatry proper.
So you get kind of some weird definitions.
Like all of a sudden, everybody's a pallagian.
Now everything's an idol.
Who could I be talking about anyway?
So.
These idol accusations of idolatry, sorry.
Yes.
Wow.
I know.
That's getting towards the top.
I'd like to apologize to our more sensitive listeners
for that comment.
So
So one of the, and we mentioned this last time, but one of the sort of classic bad definitions
is that you worship a picture of a thing instead of the thing, right?
And really, you only get this argument from even very modern iconoclasm, right?
I caught a clasm proper in the 8th and 9th centuries, but like...
modern Protestant iconoclasm usually, which is the idea that well, if you have an icon,
if you have an image of Jesus, if you have a picture of Jesus, and you venerate that,
you kiss it, you reference it, you bow to it, you're bowing to the picture instead of
to Jesus, right?
Right.
The picture gets between you and him.
Kind of thing.
Right.
Yeah.
I'm sure I've commented on this show at Zappoy before that's like
seeing a guy pick up the picture of his wife from his desk and kiss it and saying he's having an
affair with a coated two-ply piece of Bristol paper. He loves that picture not his wife. I saw him
making out with it, right? You think that person was a loon, right? You think that person was an
absolute loon, right? Everybody would instantly know somebody picks up kisses a picture of his
wife and kids. It's because he loves his wife and kids, not the picture, right? Right.
Right. By the way, the original iconic class, what they were arguing about...
about was whether icons should be venerated the same way you
venerate the cross in the gospel book.
Yeah. Right. So they were talking about what category of
holy things icons were in. They were not talking about this
kind of silliness that they thought people were worshiping
pictures instead of what they were a picture. I don't think
any religious person, no matter how...
actually idolatrous they may be. I don't think that any religious person even says,
oh, this picture is my God. Yeah. Right. Like the pagan gods, if the pagan gods thought you were
worshiping the idol instead of them, you think they'd be upset. Right. Hey, I'm right over here.
Right. So that's not how this works. That's not how any of this works.
Yeah, so you
also get, I mean, related, we should say as an adendum to that, you also just get making a picture of God.
Right. Having a picture of God at all. So, you know, any movie where there's an actor portraying Jesus
is automatically idolatry. Right. Right. Or just having an image, sometimes even across in a worship space.
Right. That's automatically idolatry. Yep. Right. And these are real positions that people actually have too.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, right, but clearly if you take that into the ancient world, right there were images in the tabard
Ackle, but that was not idolatrous worship, right like definitionally that was opposed to the idolatrous worship of
of the nations, right? Yep
so
A more common and rightfully so since it's at least a little more sophisticated is the idea that
that idolatry is about people worshipping hunks.
What are stout? Right, and this seems to have some basis in stuff that actually is in the Bible.
A certain reading of stuff that's in the Bible. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So like, okay, well
we have a passage, and this is one of the passages I think that gets used for this. And I'm just
going to read it real quick. This is from Isaiah 44. This is verses 9 through 17.
All who fashion idols are nothing and the things they
delight in, do not profit. Their witnesses neither see nor know that they may be put to shame.
Who fashions a God or casts an idol that is profitable for nothing? Behold, all his companions
shall be put to shame and the craftsmen are only human. Let them assemble, let them stand
forth. They shall be terrified. They shall be put to shame together. The ironsmith takes
a cutting tool and works it over the coals. He fashions it with hammers and works it with
his strong arm. He becomes hungry and his strength fails. He drinks no water and his
the
Carpenter stretches a line, he marks it out with a pencil, he shapes it with planes and marks it with a compass
He shapes it into the figure of a man with the beauty of a man to dwell in a house
He cuts down cedars or he chooses a cypress tree or an oak and lets it grow strong among the trees of the forest
He plants a cedar and then rain nourishes it then it becomes fuel for a man
He takes a part of it and warms himself. He candles a fire and bakes bread
Also, he makes a god and worships it. He makes it an idol and falls down before it
half of it he burns
the fire over the half he eats meat, he roasts it in a satisfied. Also he warms himself and says,
aha, I am warm. I have seen the fire. And the rest of it, he makes into a god, his idol,
and falls down to it and worships it. He prays to it and says, deliver me for you are my god.
So the one reading of this is, you know, this guy made this thing and that's his god, right?
right? And that's where the piece of wood or metal would. Yeah. And that's
and that's what the Bible is talking about here.
But that's not actually what this is all about.
What is going on in this passage, Father?
Right. Not if we read it carefully.
And so we start out with talking about these witnesses.
So these witnesses show up and they tell you about this God.
They tell you about Bale and all his escapades
and about how he went into...
and he defeated Yom and he defeated Lothan and totally won.
I'm in the other world, Fadeh, totally won again.
And then Bill says, it tells you the whole story.
Now, the people who tell you these stories weren't there,
didn't see it happen.
Right.
Don't actually know anything about it, but they're repeating the story.
So, these guys say, oh, great.
I'm going to worship Bale now.
goes.
Yeah, and either he gets metal, right?
And he has a craftsman, you know, gets the tools, you know, hammers the metal, works the metal,
working over the coals, right, or the carpenter goes, he cuts down a mighty tree and he, you know, cuts the wood
and goes and he makes himself a fire and makes himself some food and he warms himself
and takes care of his self-right works on it.
finally, you know, he's got this idol now. It says.
this is this this God is going to deliver him now.
Notice how much time Isaiah spends describing this whole process right?
Yeah.
spelling all of these trees are the different kinds of trees.
Yeah, I mean the hero of this passage, so to speak, is the craftsman.
Right.
It's describing the craftsman's deeds.
So he's heard about all these great deeds of bail, which don't, you know, by the way,
nobody was there.
We don't have any actual eyewitness testimony, but you know, be that as it may.
But that he goes, it does all these things, all these very impressive things.
And he takes care of himself while he's doing it. It provides for himself.
Right? He play it's this tree, the rain nourishes it and it grows and he cuts it to
and all of these things. And now he's got this little statue and this little statue is going to do what for him.
Right. Right. He is way more powerful than this statue.
Because the statue couldn't cut down the tree. The statue couldn't make the tree grow. The statue couldn't
couldn't, you know, make bread.
for him, the statue did nothing for him. He did everything for the statue. Right. But now he
thinks somehow the statue is going to save him or help him or yeah. Yeah. And and the point,
you know, being also that if this God that he's worshiping is so great with this statue, then why
is it that he has to do all this work in order to make this even possible? You know, like he's
clearly more powerful than the God because he can do all these things. You know, the God can't even
and if his statue falls over, he can't even pick it up.
Right, Isaiah says in another place, you know, Jeremiah, Jeremiah, who says, you know,
you have to then put fasteners down because if it tips over, it can't stand itself back
up.
But it's going to give you victory in battle.
Sure thing.
Right.
Quink, wink, nudge, nudge.
So this is about the weakness and powerlessness of the God.
Right.
Is the criticism that's taking place here.
not implying that he's actually worshiping the piece of wood.
Right. He knows it's a piece of wood. He cut it, right? He's using that piece of wood to worship this God.
And it's that God that's a worthless one, right? As we talked about at the beginning.
So yeah, there's,
we could sum up a bunch of these, right? A bunch of these sort of bad definitions
under the category of just, you know, physical objects being used.
in religious ways.
Yeah, I think this to me is one of the unspoken doctrines
of at least major parts of Protestantism
is holiness does not reside in physical objects.
That's the way I summarize in my head.
And I think that's what it is.
And so if someone makes a claim that they do,
well, that's idolatry.
And so it could be that you're using the object
in a particular religious way,
that you're making a pilgrimage to the object,
that you're...
You know on you know giving honor to the object
You know or whatever it might be right? It's all kind of groups together in this sense of like you know
No, don't do woo woo stuff with these these holy looking things because that's idolatry
Right, so there's that's another kind of category of that but right. I mean there's a lot it's clear from the Bible that physical objects
can have holiness
associated with them and religious things are done with them. I mean like
This happens about
a lot of times, both in the old and new test.
Yeah.
And in some pure and extreme, you even get that the sacraments are somehow idolatry because
their material thinks.
Right.
If you treat them as anything other than just, you know, a kind of analogy, right?
Or something.
Right.
If you have any view of any reality to the sacraments or what they do, that is leaning into idolatry
for some of the extreme end of that point of view.
again.
makes no sense in terms of the actual idolatry,
actually existing idolatry in the ancient world.
We're gonna get to that in just a second.
Yeah.
So the last sort of view,
it's sort of a less of view of,
less a definition of idolatry and more a way in which
idolatry is talked about,
which is a kind of analogical way.
Yeah.
Or at least sophisticated folks would acknowledge
that it's an analogy.
two ancient idolatry. They wouldn't try and say this is what ancient idolatry was, but they would say
this is a modern form of idolatry related by analogy and that's that it's sort of
material goods, the good things of the material world, the good things of the world. Right? Yes. So stuff you care about stuff you focus on
Yeah, the stuff you like. Yeah. Yeah, that's that's your your idol. So
So, you know, as I said earlier to you today, if you have your bell-biv-t-
bo-poster, right on your wall. Michael Bivens is your idol, right? And...
You know, you know, for my graduating class at the prom, which I did not go to, I sort
of attended a party that protested the prom, because that's the kind of 17-year-old I
was. That checks out. Yeah. It's so hard to say goodbye to yesterday was the theme for
our class. So, so you
might be. Well, I guess that's better than not. I'm not
going to live to vote. It's better than having the theme be
poison, I guess. Right. Allow me to be the first first person in
AFR history to say over their airwaves, you can't trust a big
button of smile. Anyway. So this this is just the yeah, that so
so anything you like any of the goods of this world that you
like that you care about that are important to you. Even if they
We have...
haven't been on American Idol, then that is in some way idolatry.
Right.
And this is not totally wrong.
There is a sense in which this is correct.
And we're going to come back to that at the very end of the third half tonight.
But the casual way it's bound bandied about is showing a bunch of people with clato brain.
And that's not play-doh brain, like the stuff you ate when you were three, even though
you weren't supposed to.
Not me.
But play-doh, the philosopher.
And there's this idea from play-doh that distinction implies opposition.
Right.
So if you have more than one thing, they're automatically to some degree opposed to each
other.
So if God is the ultimate good, anything you like other than God, anything you care about,
anything you invest in other than God.
is somehow taking away from your love and care and investment in God.
Right. And I mean, and this is this is the basis also for one of the objections about
like asking, you know, the help of saints like, like, why do you need to spend time in that?
Just ask God, you know, you know, you don't need to take away from, you know, your question.
It's interesting how it's it plays out in almost exactly the same way.
Right. Right. And yeah, that's just that's just Plato brain.
Man, you're so...
about that. More than one thing could be good. More than one thing could be good and more than one
thing could be bad. But you have to have good things that are proper in a proper order. Yeah, exactly.
In the right way. Okay. So, so how does idolatry actually then work? Like what is the technique?
Because it is a technique, right? Right. Yeah, it's a practice. Yeah. Yeah. It's something you do.
you idolatry, you do it idolatry.
No. So we've talked before, a little bit of a little bit of review catch up again, right?
Of the idea that an idol is strictly speaking a body for a God or a body for a spirit.
And that's true in a couple of senses, right? So the most sort of pardon the pun would in sense is
that you have the spirit that is inside it, right?
Sort of into.
it as a body. Right? Yeah. We've talked about the the ritual for the opening of the nostrils that
allows the spirit to go into the out. So it is dwelling within it. Like Robotech. Ghost in the machine.
So but it's also and more importantly true in the broader sense of body that we've talked about on
on the show that sees a body.
the nexus of powers and potentialities.
So it is like Robotech.
Sort of.
Which has to say, I'm trying to get you to acknowledge
which back cross season are we talking about?
Oh yeah, no, you've lost me now.
I think it's more like the motorcycles than the planes.
Anyway.
Yeah, although there's a trotty, a kind of giants.
Oh, this may require an episode.
Anyway.
so
That means that what we're doing, well not what we're doing hopefully, but what someone
is doing, what they make an idol is they're creating a hypostasis, they're creating a localization
for the God in question.
Yeah, so the worshipper can interact with the God and the God can interact with the worshipper
through this thing.
Right, and so for, we talked before, we were talking about hypostasis and how that works
and that there is a pagan conception of it, that one of the chord just
jumps between the God of Israel and the pagan gods is that the pagan gods can have hypothetically
an infinite number of hypostases. Yeah, just keep making idols because you can make them. Yeah,
yeah. Whereas the difference is that you know where the God of Israel has eternally existed in
three hypostases and that's it and you can't make them and you can't, right? But so you're making
this body, this localization of
the God and that's why you get not just sort of an identification of, for example,
Artemis of the Ephesians, right? But Artemis of the Ephesians has a particular idol, a particular image
that looks very different than the Artemis you'd find in the Peloponnes.
Hmm right very different. Yeah right. So so it
It's actually a sort of unique and local sort of form of the God, where a particular people,
whether that be a family, a clan, a tribe, a city, right, whatever social unit, can then sort of,
it's an access point for them to that spirit, right, where they can go and richially then share
hospitality, communion, communion with that spirit. Right. Right. And so, you know, if you're thinking
you
listener about the golden calf incident where Moses is up on Sinai and you know
wow he seems to be gone for a long time I guess he's gone you know and and
Aaron leads the people in worshiping making and then worshiping the golden calf
this is an attempt to worship Yahweh their true God by means of this image
You
Right. Because notice when it's presented in front of everybody, Aaron says,
Here's the God that brought you up out of Egypt. You know, he's not saying this golden calf brought you up out of Egypt
But essentially let's use this golden calf in an idolatrous way in an attempt to
Interact with Yahweh our God, right? So it's it's trying to worship
their God the only God worthy of worship
by idolatrous means.
That's what's going on there. That's why he says, you know, here's the God that brought you up out of Egypt.
But it's, you know, if you take a close look at all the things that God does tell them to do in terms of
worshiping him, there is no point at which any object
anywhere in the Tabernacle or the temple, not even the Ark of the Covenant is described as being a body
of Yahweh. And there is no idol that God can
men's them to make and use.
Right?
Although there is a really interesting note about the arc of the covenant father that you
brought up when we were briefing about this related day.
So I mean, why'd you still be ready about that?
Yeah, this is, I mean, this is something that especially stands out.
So some people seem to think that the arc of the covenant was like, like God lived inside
of it.
Like it was a box that God lived in.
Yeah.
And no.
Now.
I mean, how many times does he say he does not dwell?
It's tough made by hands.
Yeah, let alone a box.
Yeah, here around on poles.
So, and yeah, we'll cook down that rabbit trail now.
Self-discipline.
But I don't see any indian adjoins in my head right now, though.
Oh, that's not where I was going at all.
It's beautiful.
It's all right.
Sorry.
Yeah.
I don't think that was supposed to be god.
I don't know.
Who that was about that?
I don't even look like K-Vat.
Yeah, I think it was supposed to be like the angel of death or something like that in
that film.
Yeah.
That film scared the snot out of me when I was a little kid.
Boy.
Nothing like seeing Nazis face melt.
That's right.
Yeah.
I mean, if Indiana Jones wasn't punching Nazis, he was melting their faces.
Anyway.
So where we're going with this though is that...
The Ark of the Covenant is not sort of this one-off item that didn't exist anywhere else
in the world.
It's similar to a kind of bark, a kind of ceremonial boat, ritual boat that was either
carried or sent on an actual boat down the Nile in Egypt.
And the key difference, though, is that those, you may remember the Ark has the two carovine
with their wings extended over the center.
The barks would usually have two goddesses, usually ISIS and nethus, who were winged.
Sometimes they were just depicted in bird form, but sometimes they were sort of humanoid
women with wings extended across the middle.
But then the idol of the god, or the image of us was used on a tomb or that kind of thing,
image of the dead Pharaoh who of course was a god, right? The image of the God would be between the wings.
Right. And in the case of the Ark of the Covenant, there's nothing there.
Yeah, so it's a very similar shape. You have the winged spirits on either end, but in the middle,
nothing, no idle. Yeah, no idle. So the Ark of the Covenant was a constant pointer that there was not,
right actually an idol there.
I can't remember who it was was it was an antichy sapifanese when he invaded the temple and
or in taking of of
Pompey. Yeah, yeah, he invades the temple and you know shoves his way into the holy of holies and
then there's no idol there and he's like what's going on? What's this all about? Yeah,
there's nothing there. Yeah, and he's he told the Romans that that started this huge fascination
with Judaism.
Yeah, among upper class Romans because they decided that the Jews must worship their God's solo mentees
Yes, only with their minds with their mind. It's seen very sophisticated
It's strange so philosophical those that that Judaism yeah
um, so yeah
um
And a lot of those people were Saint Paul's first Gentile converts later, so that'll work out. Yeah, okay. That worked out
work out so well for Pompey long term, but anyway, that's another story. So idols then are
are something that's used to localize the God, meaning it's a sort of it's a sort of spiritual
technology used for purposes of worship, right? So what kind of forms then do idols take? Well,
Obviously, like, statuaries really obvious, right?
Right.
That's probably...
your typical idol, that's what people think of with it, think of idols.
But also very common, probably maybe even more common in the ancient world,
where sacred trees and poles,
ashras being the most famous pole, biblically, probably.
Usually within some kind of there grow,
some kind of grove or like a, sometimes like a little walled garden or grove.
Yeah, you would segment off a sacred space around it.
Yeah, and we made a discovery
During our pre-show briefing. Oh, yes, this is amazing because I
was
drinking some of the bold and refreshing
Sunny delight
And we discovered that it is entirely possible that Sunny D may be an idol
because on the side of the bottle as I perused it was
Oh
legend of Sunny D. Talking about how in the summer of 1963 two men stood in Florida
in Orange Grove, perhaps a sacred Orange Grove. And there they took a vow, an oath, to make
the boldest, most refreshing citrus drink, but the world had ever seen. And that's what
produce SunnyD. So it is entirely possible that SunnyD is an idol. I don't...
know for what God you figured out. But just a tidbit you could verify that.
Blood orange. Yeah, you verify that on the side of any current bottle of sunny
delight and since it's cold and flu season, get your vitamin C kids. So in
addition to the sacred trees and poles citrus and otherwise another very very
common form of idol or image.
that we don't often think of is amulets or sort of,
it's an amulet if you're wearing it around your neck
or around your hand, but small insets on the insides
or outsides of buildings, sort of medallion insets carved
are incredibly common throughout the ancient world.
One of the most common ones in the Greek and Roman
Roman worlds was to have a Medusa head, an image of a Medusa head.
Which may seem weird, like to walk around with that around your neck, right, or if you're
a Jew and Galilee, to put that on the outside of your synagogue as many of the Galilee
and synagogues did, they had multiple Medusa heads facing in different directions.
But the idea here was...
And that was bad by the way.
Yeah, yeah, that was not a good thing.
that they did that on those synagogues. Now note that they had them on the outside, not the inside,
but still. It was Galilee of the Gentiles for a reason. But so the story of Medusa, Medusa is this
priestess who is super beautiful and a little bit vain, and so gets cursed by the gods because
That's they do that and
So she becomes right to mature
So no one now can look at her, right, without getting turned to stone and dying.
So one of the common things in ritual as a whole, that we won't go too deep into this, but is that you,
you reenact or you depict something in order to ward it off.
Yeah.
Right. This is a real rabbit trail, so I'm not going down it, but this is actually how Aristotle's
poetics works and makes sense in terms of his understanding.
of Greek tragedy. But so Medusa is sort of this image of someone who had something really
bad happen to her, right? She got cursed, right? And she gets... So the image of Medusa was
seen to ward off like ill fate, right? And it curses that other people might direct at you.
Yeah. So you sort of depict a curse to ward off a curse was sort of the general idea. But there
There were amulets and that kind of thing.
picked a lot of things for these various reasons that were used in these sort of idolatrous
ways, a sort of an access point to spiritual powers.
Yeah, so the thing that this kind of reminded me of, like having Medusa heads on the outside
of buildings to, like, ward off evil, the thing that reminded me of actually was gargoyles.
And so I looked up, I was like, okay, what is the deal with gargoyles?
And it seems that originally Gargo is even on the outside and the worst...
We're used to them being like on Gothic cathedrals, right?
But actually, Gargoyle heads, particularly heads, were also depicted on the outside of
other kinds of buildings, too.
It was not just churches.
So here's what I discovered.
Originally most Gargoyles were just the head and the neck of a dragon.
And later on you get the kind of bat light, human bat.
Whereback there you go, a whereback sort of looking thing, but eventually it initially
it's just heads and necks of dragons.
And this seems to come from a seventh century or so legend about St. Romano's of Hué in
France that he defeated a dragon that was terrorizing the people by making use of a cross
to defeat it.
And so they they dragged the body back and they were going to burn the whole thing, which
they did but they
head in the neck because it had been sort of so galvanized by the fire of the dragon
did not burn. And so St. Romano's hung up the neck in the head on the outside of the church,
essentially, as a kind of a warning to other demons. Like, you know, if you come around here,
this is what's going to happen to you. And so there is, I mean, it is kind of weirdly parallel,
But it's more like putting the heads of your enemies on.
spikes outside the gate kind of thing than this sense of that this face is going to itself
sort of ward off evil, you know. But there is a certain kind of curious parallel to that.
No, we do not have any gargoyles in the outside of our church here in Amaz. Just FY.
But if someone wants to donate one, I'll talk, I'll submit it to the Paris Council. Yeah.
So, Bishop, thanks.
Right, exactly.
Yeah, so those being sort of the types of idols then, where do you find that idols?
And of course there's some obvious ones, right? So you've got temples, that's a big, right?
Yeah, at the center point of a temple as we've talked about before, you have the image of the God.
But then you also will find them in shrines and what separates a shrine from a temple is generally
that shrines are at some natural feature.
Okay, the grove, the spring.
Right.
a cleft in the rock, right?
Some kind of place that's associated with spiritual activity,
where there's been some kind of spiritual encounter
in the past, as we've talked about before.
And then that will be a place where a shrine is built
because it's seen as sort of being a natural access point.
And then that will usually have images brought into it.
And then probably the most important one,
but the one we think about the least
is that at the center of every home, for example,
the first.
century AD, you had a hearth, right? And at that hearth, that hearth, especially in Roman
religion, was the most important part of the home, right? Right in the middle. And that
would be the place where you had what are sometimes called in the Bible, the household
gods, right? You would have the small idols or images of the gods of the family, the
the encestors, the place where
where you lived, the place where you used to live,
your trade guild, all sort of collected there,
who are sort of your gods.
And it's important to mention, what is a hearth?
I mean, that's the place where all the food gets prepared.
That's the place you gather around for warmth.
Like it really is a major, major place in your home.
And probably there's eating going on right there as well,
because the food is hot off the hearth
and you eat it right there.
Right, there's a-
reason why Isaiah talked about kittling a fire for warmth making food and then there's also
idols. Yeah, because it all happens in one spot. Yeah, yeah. And this is the gathering
place for the family. This is where family interactions with each other, prayer, all
that kind of thing is is going to happen, right? So, the the origin of what we would now
now called an icon corner, a prayer corner in an orthodox house is with
with the purification of this, the removal of the idols from this family gathering place
and the replacing of them with the icon of Christ, first and foremost, and then later
also of the saints who are not, as we've talked about many times, not just subins for
other pagan gods but
are the saints at glory who have actually replaced those fallen pagan gods. Yeah, defeated them.
Right. And so I'm going to suggest, right, that it's interesting to note,
it's second Corinthians four verse six, St. Paul talks about seeing the face of Jesus Christ. He
speaks in a way that suggests that the Christians and
Corridors.
the face of Jesus Christ. Right? And when I say he conveys that they've seen it, he's using a
reference to the glory of God in the face of Jesus Christ as a way of not materializing but making
the idea that the power of God is made real for them in the face of Jesus Christ. Right? That's the
place where they see it. Right. And so if they haven't ever actually
seen the face of Jesus Christ in Corinth. His argument doesn't work so well. Right, because Jesus
never went to Corinth. Right, anywhere near. So that implies to me that we've already got something
like iconography, iconographic tradition starting. Now, if you want to say they weren't replacing those,
getting rid of those idols and replacing it with an icon of Christ in their home, that's why if you
If you want to say, hey, they were putting up by God's
oppression, they're synagogue.
I won't argue with you about that. That's a final alternative. I think less likely
The local synagogue would be putting up by gods of Christ that Christians would have them in their homes, but okay
But it is a strong argument that something's happening there. I think
Yeah
All right, well, we've just kind of gone through the
The hardware and the location so to speak of idolatry and
And when we get back...
after our break in just a moment in the third half,
we're gonna be talking about
what exactly does idolatry do to you.
So we will be right back after this break.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Are you curious about the Orthodox Christian faith?
Do you have questions about Orthodox Christianity that you can't trust strangers and internet
forums to answer?
Are you an Orthodox Christian looking for a reliable first place to send your interested friends?
Do you need help finding an Orthodox church near you?
My name is Father Paul Hodg.
I serve in the Antiochian Orthodox Christian Archdiocese of North America.
My name is Father Joseph Lupe.
I serve in the Orthodox Church in America.
My name is Father Anthony Cook.
I serve in the Greek Orthodox Archdiocese of America.
And I'm Father Andrew Stephen James,
a chief content officer of ancient faith ministries
and a priest of the Antioffan Archediocese.
And where the Orthodox intro team?
If you're looking for a first stop online
to get an introduction to the Orthodox faith,
a place to get answers to questions from qualified Orthodox Christian clergy,
A place to send your friend.
and not just toss them into the chaos of the internet.
A place to get help finding an Orthodox parish
and get plugged into an actual Orthodox community.
Then point your web browser at Orthodoxintro.org.
Orthodoxintro.org is a free service of ancient faith ministries
and made possible by our donors.
It's an Orthodox on-ramp to the Christian life.
Again, that's Orthodoxintro.org.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Welcome back.
It's the third half of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
So I like that commercial that's got a good beat.
Thank you. Thank you.
I don't know if you could dance to it,
but I feel there was a missed opportunity
when you guys all introduced yourselves
that you didn't say after that
and by our powers combined,
we are Orthodox intro.org.
I feel like that was a strike you should not have let past.
You should have swung.
Well, yeah, thank you for that note.
All right, well, before we get to
exactly what idolatry does for you, so to speak,
or to you really.
We do have a caller and Sal is calling in.
So Sal, welcome to the Lord of Spears podcast.
Thank you, fathers.
Can you hear me?
We hear you.
What's on your mind?
I was reading in the life of St. McCarrie,
the Spirit Bearer and the other Desert Fathers,
that when they go out to the desert,
It seems to be that the demons don't follow them there.
But that's kind of the demon hang out.
And they mention a lot of times, like, hey, we're going to get this macarons out.
Whoever whoever, they're making a paradise of our desert.
And then you read in the Gospel where God says when you, the Christ says when you banish a demon to go into dry and deserted places.
And then you combine that thought with the idea of sending the goat out to the desert, as a evil.
And then you combine that idea with the idea of like,
Tows in Mexico having these weird, like, spiritual dark-
to it and the American Southwest and all that type of stuff.
And there seems to be a connection with the demonic
and the actual physical desert.
And am I reading too much into that?
Or is that something that yeah,
that's kind of where they chill.
I mean, that is definitely a thing.
You get that in the Bible and there's that idea
that they're described as wandering spirits
and usually that's the place where...
you encounter them. I mean when I recall correctly when Jesus is tempted he goes
into a wilderness place and he's confronted by the devil. Father what do you
have to say about this? Well the quote Val Kilmer's greatest film role. You don't
want to go to the desert. So anybody who gets that reference I'll have to
figure out so I've got a prize to give them.
immediate family members are disqualified.
So, yeah, the wilderness for Israel, we've talked about paradise,
remember this walled garden that God has put in order and filled with life.
And so the contrast with that, the opposite of
that is the desert, right?
There's the wilderness, which is not put in order and is full of death, right?
There's decaying animals, dead people, right?
Scavengers beating on carrying, right?
So it is, in a sense, the outside of Eden.
That's why you get, as you point out in St. Macarius, this kind of contrast.
He by going there, right?
He sort of brings God with him, the way Adam and Eve.
we're supposed to bring God with them out of paradise into the world.
And by doing that, he's turning the wilderness into a paradise.
He's setting it with order, filling it with spiritual life.
And the demons don't like that.
Right?
Sort of happening in real time.
Now, we shouldn't take that into materialist sense.
Right?
Like don't go to Arizona.
But.
but uh...
i believe he's single that new mexico
earlier actually. Yeah, but I mean, breaking bad bitter
coleslaw, come on, good television. Anyway, yeah, this so we
should take into that kind of materialist, but it's sort of if
a garden, right, an ordered, tended garden that's full of life
and beauty, if that's our idea of where God lives, then you
could pretty quickly see how the wilderness, the desert is
to be P. Antithesis.
of that, right? Sort of a wasteland is the opposite of that. But the response to that is
not to just never go there. The response is to try to go there and bring God there as the
desert fathers did. Does that make sense, so?
Hello? Speak to us.
So, oh, I think we lost him.
Who did this to you?
All right, well, hopefully that makes some sense.
I was like, look at my instruments,
like did I just lose everybody?
But then I heard your voice and it was okay.
Okay.
Well, that's the most romantic thing you've ever sent to me.
I'll take that in these Shakespearean sense
of a romance, you know, like the tempest and that kind of thing.
So, all right.
Well, hopefully that was helpful to-
to sell. So we're going to take one more caller. We have father Elijah calling. So father Elijah, are you there?
I am here.
Welcome.
He isn't always so be welcome to Lord of Spears podcast father. What's on your mind?
Well, I was fascinated, you know, just listening with my family.
I hope I think we lost Father.
Finally, technical difficulties that aren't mine.
Yeah, there he goes.
All right, well, I'm going to try again.
So Father Lager, you're there.
We lost you for a second.
Oh, okay.
Well, so if we can get him back, you know,
So, Matyska Trudy just let us know if he comes back.
I'll just ask one more time. Father Lijer, are you there?
I lost your first.
Oh, are you there, Father?
This is my name is Frank.
Oh, okay. Well,
all right. We're going to move. We're going to move on here until we get things
worked worked out over there with the call board. So that could have been the Pope.
Really? You think the Pope would call and say hi. My name is Frank.
I don't know. I don't see.
He's low key. I don't know it.
It didn't sound Argentinian.
Gubs off is hot.
I don't know.
I'd have a lot to say to them.
Yeah, that's true.
We could just set aside the rest of the episode to have a conversation with the Pope.
All right, well, so, okay, idolatry.
We've talked about what you need to, what someone, what they used for idolatry and where
you located and all that kind of thing.
So, you know, we...
We talked about setting them up, taking care of it.
We've talked about a lot of this stuff before, the opening of the nostril ceremony,
and of course putting food in front of it, this kind of stuff.
What's the point?
Does it actually have some kind of effect on the worshipers?
That's what we're talking about here in the third half.
What's going on with that, Father?
The answer is yes.
I can't say good night and that be funny at this point because it's already been two hours.
So this is your brain on idolatry.
This is the, yeah.
So, and this is sort of laid out to us, right?
So the Old Testament isn't against idolatry
just because God decided he didn't like it, right?
And so we put it on the rules like none of that in this house, right?
Get out of this house if those are the clothes you're going to wear.
Get out of this house if you don't cut that hair.
Right. It's not like that kind of rule.
It's because idolatry does something to humans
when they do it. Right.
Because all worship has a transformative effect
on the worshipper. Right. Right.
So that's kind of telegraphed in Psalm 115
in the Hebrew 114 if you're reading the Greek
versus three through eight.
Okay. So what that says,
Starting with
three, our God is in the heavens. He does all that he pleases. Their idols are silver and gold
the work of human hands. They have mouths, but do not speak eyes, but do not see. They have ears,
but do not hear noses, but do not smell. They have hands, but do not feel a feet, but do not walk,
and they do not make a sound in their throat. Those who make them become like them so do all who
trust in them. Right and so the
contrast here is with that second part of verse three, right? Our God who is in the heavens,
he does all that he pleases, he does whatever he wants, he's all powerful, right? And
these gods who are being worshipped by means of idols don't really do much of anything.
Right? They have things done to them, right? They're created, they're cared for, they do,
The things happen to them, but they don't do anything.
Right. And then the same thing is going to happen to those who follow them. So we have to do a little bit of our
step back in quick review here.
We've talked before about how
language, art and music and ritual are ways that we as humans engage with
the world and things that shape our human consciousness,
shape the world around this in terms of how we
experience it. Right. And so idolatry is a form of ritual. But that includes obviously art in
crafting the idol can include music in the worship language in the worship, right. And so participating
in idolatry using idolatry as your mode of worship and your mode of interacting with the spiritual
world is going to shape beyond just that act. It's not just a side, but it's going to shape.
how you view other people, how you view the world around you and objects in it, how you view the divine,
your view of God or the gods. Yeah. And how you relate to and interact with all of these things.
Yeah, how you treat everybody. So yeah. Okay. So apparently we have Father Elijah back. So Father
I just are you there?
I'm here. Are you here? I'm here.
Okay, I'm all the way over here.
Oh yes, we're all in different places.
Where is there?
No.
Yes, I was very fascinated by the talk about the ancient rule that the hearth's played in
homes.
Right.
And that that would be kind of the gathering of the household idols.
And that was also kind of the social and spatial center of the home.
A lot of...
and architecture are living rooms are kind of the center of the home.
Often a living room is now merging with the kitchen and often in the middle of all of it will be a
really wonderful place with outlets to plug in a television. And I'm an orthodox priest now,
but I grew up a Protestant and I know in the Protestant language of idolatry we love to materialize
our idolatry and we love to talk about worshiping the television.
and work-shipping technology.
And I was wondering in the Peugeot being,
you know, Jonathan Peugeot talks about,
how sometimes worship and attention go together.
I'm just wondering, you know, in your thoughts
of this interaction of the center of the home,
historically being a place where idols would be,
now we have technology.
How do we just, you know, pull apart, you know,
attention to things that maybe grab our desire
our attention and those
that are spiritually malificent and seeking to more classical, maybe old gods versus new
gods, the classic paganism, classic idolatrys versus maybe these new spin of idol, new spin
on idols and attention. Does that just make any sense? I'm sorry.
Yeah, I think so. In fact, in some ways, I think you're sort of setting up for the conclusion
of this podcast.
Uh, I'm sorry.
No, no, no.
That's good.
But I mean, I can't speak for the way that Jonathan Peugeot
would address this.
Not that you were asking that in particular,
but you mentioned him.
I mean, I will just say this.
Well, one, it's interesting actually,
I think that more and more family gathered around a television
set is not hardly even a thing.
More and more.
It's people's gathered each separately
around his or her own device.
You know, we've all got...
the Wi-Fi password, right? So there's, I think there is some truth to that. The only thing I'll say,
though, is that attention is definitely an element in worship, so it's a necessary condition, but
it's not sufficient, right? So just paying attention to something does not mean that you're worshipping
it, right? Or idolizing it. You know, but definitely there.
is like I think you are onto something in my opinion that what you pay your attention to
and I have always loved that expression, that attention in English is something we pay,
right? Like you have a finite amount of it. You can't pay attention to everything all the time.
You know, that what you pay your attention to does transform you.
You know, like it's you know one of the classic pieces of pastoral advice to someone who has
Trouble battling lustful thoughts is you know control your eyes dude
Right, you know, I'm sure you've just experienced that in the priesthood right like control your eyes
What are you looking at what are you listening to you know that kind of thing?
So so there is some truth to that and I think that the way that idolatry works is it it really
I don't believe.
It's that part.
like you're really going into communion with the thing that you are engaging in idolatrous worship of.
You know, like it's one thing to contemplate an image of some false God.
It's another thing to actually put food in front of it and then eat some of that food.
Yeah, that's very helpful because in my before, in the before years,
in the before years when I was there before times.
Missionary, my before time.
And as a Protestant missionary, I live amongst a lot of people in Southeast Asia that literally
would sacrifice food and chickens to idols.
And growing up Protestant, there was a lot of this talk of attention.
And I was like, you know, it doesn't seem that when I'm paying too much attention to my
phone or to the TV that I'm doing what they're doing, there might be an overlap, but there
is a distinction.
So yeah.
Yeah, I mean, you saw real idolatry.
Like that's the real deal.
you saw you know putting food in front of images and then eating parts.
of it that is pretty much the key movement in idolatrous worship.
A father Steven, do you have anything you wanted to add or I'm actually or I'm not going
to I'm actually.
Oh, thank God.
Yeah, I mean, I don't know if it's idolatry per se, but any opportunity I get to kind of
talk badly about our current cultural media landscape.
I'll take.
And as we talk on a part.
podcast. Yeah.
Yeah.
Geedabords said decades ago that everything that used to be directly experienced is now
presented to us in the form of spectacle.
And you see that every day when you see people in front of some big event watching it through
their phone.
I think in a lot of ways the state where it now is worse than the pagans.
The ancient pagans were communing with.
but at least the whole family was commuting with the same ones.
Whereas not an endorsement either way by the way.
Yeah. Whereas now, you know, you know, and 50 years ago,
it was the isolate not to go back to last episode,
but the isolated nuclear family all at least scaring at one TV.
Now everybody has their own screen.
And so each one is having this
stream of images, because that's how we receive information now is almost purely through images.
Fed into them separately on a separate stream, and each one of them is being formed by it separately,
and thereby being alienated from each other and from everyone else.
And so this is sort of profoundly anti-communal technology.
This is not just breaking down the family, but every kind of social bond that there is,
so that the only thing any individual is connected to anything through is through that conduit
of their feed.
Yeah, so I just want to be Debbie Downer.
And once again tell everybody to quit social media.
Yeah, and we've told our self this fiction that all this stuff is making our life better,
and we all know it isn't.
None of us are happier because of it.
None of us feel more connected to people because of it.
We're just fooling ourselves.
So there's going to be a crisis point at some point, barring some catastrophe that destroys
the internet and sets us all free.
I don't know which way it's going to go, but yeah, we've lost the heart.
And I think a key part, we've talked about this other show before, a key part of trying
to rebuild and come together again as families and extended family in this community has to
be rebuilding the heart at a real practical way to start with that is the prayer corner,
the icon corner.
Yeah.
I'm a big fan of almost anything.
I mean, it's interesting, you know, like...
I, I, well, I'll just back up.
I'm a big fan of almost anything that gathers together the family and focuses on a thing.
Like, it's really, really worth it to do family dinner every night if possible.
If it's not possible to give a night, you're going to do it tomorrow night, you know?
I'm a big fan of, you know, parents reading to the whole collection of kids all at once,
even the one that can't stop wiggling.
know I think these are
just such critical things that
informal generations were taken much more for granted.
And now the, you know, the atomization of
even the people living in the same house now
has really accelerated.
It looked like, you know, at the beginning of the pandemic,
it almost looked like there was maybe some reversal of that,
right?
But I don't know, I don't think it lasted,
maybe a hot minute.
Um, um,
But yeah, I think we're father Steven said is right,
we've kind of lost the hearth.
And yeah, yeah.
Does that make sense, Father?
No, it makes absolute sense.
It was when we first moved here to Northern California
and we bought our house.
There was actually a big blank, unpainted square
where the TV used to be from the previous owners.
and we intentionally actually said that.
up as our our hearth icon corner.
There you go.
I have a place technology with.
And so we have a, you know, a facing
used to one that we usually pray towards.
But we also have that, like a symbolic
birth icon corner where the TV, you know,
previously was with the previous owner.
So I really appreciate all that you've
mentioned.
Thank you so much.
And this if I could say one brief thing,
over a decade over overseas in Southeast Asia,
so much of what you've
This podcast is talked about the church or spirits and all these different things even this very episode
It is alive and well especially in Thailand and Southeast Asia and it's it's shocking how much
similarities
To what you and father's team were just talking about and what's actively going on
In Southeast Asia, so just amazing, so thank you so much. You're welcome and I'll add you know, it's it's growing here in America
people engaging in these inside.
And I think in some cases, I think it's because people are seeking out some kind of hearth,
right?
They're getting it wrong, but I think that's part of what's going on.
So well, thank you very much for calling in tonight, Father.
Thank you so much, Father.
All right.
So we were just talking about how ritual shapes who you are, especially through the elements
of it, often including language, art, and music, shapes the way that you think about
God and other people and how you interact.
with them, how you see them and so forth.
So, I mean, how does idolatry and what it does in that regard?
How does that contrast with Christianity?
Right.
Which is, the hope is that it's doing something to you as well, but functioning in a different
way and having a different result.
Right.
So, without going too far down a rabbit trail, what are the problems in understanding what
Christian quote-unquote ethics is.
is that we've inherited this thing where we divvy up the Torah somewhat arbitrarily.
Right? But in the Torah, there's no distinction between, here are the rituals by which you worship
your God. Here is the way you treat each other. Here is the way you govern your community and order
your community. Right? These are all part and parcel of the same thing. And so what we normally
think of as Christian ethics actually has a ritual dimension.
Right. We've talked about this on the show before. So when we see the scene of the last
judgment, and we're about to start the triodian, but when we see the scene of the last
judgment in Matthew 25 and the parable, the sheep and the goats, right, we're told about
what makes the sheep sheep and the goats goats, the basis of their judgment, is not what
they believed, the results of a theology test or anything else. It's what they offered
to Christ.
And it's what they offered to Christ through the least, the lowest of humanity, the poorest,
the most needy, the least able to repay.
They were the vehicle through which people made offerings to Christ or failed to make offerings
to Christ.
So this gets back to what we were talking about a little while.
the idea that humans being made in the image of God makes them icons of God, right,
that they are iconography and how this is the opposite of idolatry, right, that they are sort of conduits to
God to Christ. So when you offer a cup of cold water to a little one, right, you are offering it to
Christ, right? It is an offering to Christ in these sacrificial
sense, right?
The hospitality offered to
other humans as hospitality offered to Christ.
And so this is why we have as one of our two
paradigmatic commandments.
Love your neighbor as yourself, right?
Because and that's why it is linked.
That's what Christ says.
It is like it, right?
It is it is parallel to it.
Love the Lord your God, right?
Love your way your God.
Why?
Because those two are the same thing, right?
You love God and you love him through.
his image. Right. Which is why it says also, if a man says he loves God and hates his
brother, he's a liar. Right. You can't, you can't not do both. Right. So, idolatry then,
if we're correct, that it's an inversion, if it's the opposite of iconography. Right.
idolatry is a means of worship.
Right that is directed at controlling
spiritual forces
Right right and sort of the most gross form of this of course is ancient magic
Right, but all ancient ritual
Senator out idolatry had this same element right that the idol as this access point is the place where you can stick your lever to move deity
This is the spot where we're
I could put it and I can pull and I can bend divine forces to my will.
I could bend spiritual forces to my will.
So if I do it and I don't get the result I want, well, maybe I did the ritual wrong, right?
Maybe the priest messed up so we kill him and try again with another priest.
Yeah.
Maybe there were some Christians around who didn't participate so we kill them and try again
with another pagan ritual, right?
Right.
But there was some problem.
problem that caused the God, the God did not accept the offering and not do what we wanted.
Maybe we need to offer more.
It's very common in the ancient world to just straight out offer bribes to God to make
offers to them.
We even see that in scripture, the story of Jeff, the not the part with his, well, it does
include his daughter, but when he makes the vow, right, he's kind of offering God, hey,
If you give me victory then...
whoever runs out and it is whoever in the text whoever runs out to CBL sacrifice to you
in judges right sort of offering trying to make a deal right yeah with the human sacrifice
and this kind of instrumentality is the opposite of love right right right because because love
sets free love functions and freedom love is not about trying to control anybody i mean that's not
That would love does it.
doesn't control. Right. If you're trying to manipulate God and get him to do what you want,
that's not the same as loving him. And that's humility. It's not. Yeah. And that's the difference
between prayer and magic. That's right. And we've talked about before how sometimes people try
to use prayer as magic. Right. Well, if I just pray hard enough, they get enough people to pray
and pray the right prayer. Right. They got to do what I want. That's not prayer now. That's magic.
Right? That's ritual magic is where you're
you're heading with that, right?
But so if that's how you view God or the gods, if that's how you view the divine, if
that's how you view the spiritual realm, right?
How is that going to bleed over into how you view other people and how you view things
in the world?
Right.
And also, you know, if you read the actual stories of these gods, this is the way they
act.
These are the exemplars.
As I think we pointed out on this podcast.
as before, you know, if your society worships Zeus, what does it do to your society when
your most high God is a serial rapist? You know, that's the ultimate in, you know, being
in your society is this kind of being.
Yeah. And your queen of the gods is just vengeful and jealous and constantly sort of hysterical
and rage for not intended. Right? Right.
Right. Right. This is this then shapes how these people participate, these rituals and it's reaffirmed and their
culture is reshaped every time they do these rituals. Right. The person who goes and casts a love spell is not
only trying to manipulate spiritual forces, they're trying to manipulate another human. Right.
Into giving them what they want. Right. And so this is an idolatry at its core represents an approach
to the spiritual world and even the material world because those are going to bleed over into each other based on instrumentality
based on seizing control of the levers, right?
Taking control of fate by one means or another, right?
Through an exercise of power and expertise and technique, I am going to become the master of my own destiny.
This is where we can now wrap around to get to talk about
about the way in which material goods, things like money,
can be talked about in terms of idolatry.
We talked earlier about how,
at the beginning of the second half,
that could sometimes be done in sort of a hackneyed way,
right, where it's just like,
oh, if you think about anything other than God,
you should be thinking about God, right?
That sort of, right.
Plotonic idea.
But the goods of this world,
the good things of this world can be viewed
this sort of instrument.
way. So an example from Scripture is when Christ tells the parable of the rich
fool, right? He has this big harvest, so he builds more barns, he fills them up.
He says, ah, now I have all this food. I can now take my leisure, I can retire, I
can enjoy good things for the rest of my life. He thinks because of his wealth and
success, he now has command of his life, right? And he's then called a fool
because he's going to die that night.
Right?
Right. And so his money, his wealth, his planning, all of that did not allow him to seize control
of the forces of the universe, did not allow him to seize control of his fate. And so for him,
that wealth and planning and success were idolatry, right. He was participating in idolatry because
he was using them as the lever. Yeah. And like all idolatry, it just proves that the lever is garbage,
It doesn't actually do what it claims to be able to do.
Right.
It's less powerful than the person who's trusting in it.
Yeah.
It's interesting.
I mean, you think about even now, like this has happened, maybe not enough, but it's
happened a number of times in recent years that we see people who are ridiculously wealthy
and powerful that lose they lose it all and they end up in jail or dead or or or you
know, whatever it might be.
proving this again the parable the rich fool.
that just because you have all the whatever in the world does not mean that you're going to get the results that you want, you know, you have...
I mean, how many times does it say in Scripture that the people who are in places of power are there because God has allowed them to be?
That the people who have things have them because God has given them to them.
You know, it's emphasized over and over again.
Right. And so over and over again in liturgy, right? In Christian worship because it's about love.
It's about offering.
ourselves and everything we have and everything we are to God and also offering all that to our neighbor
right who is in need. That's the opposite of trying to take control of God or take control of our
neighbor. Yeah and I mean it's notable in ancient pagan culture that social stratification was
considered absolutely the norm and that if you were above another person it was completely
correct and right and normal and natural for you to
to step on that other person and make use of them because you were in the position that you were in because the gods had put you there and
It was normal that you should treat other people as less than you and and in many cases is not even being people
I mean, that's the way that the whole ethics of the ancient world worked was based on this
Web of manipulation and control and people stepping on each other's faces
Right, right. And we can approach it, you know, to use the language I say I used.
Right. What is it that you're counting on to save you to deliver you when everything goes wrong?
Are you planning on, well, I've got a lot of money saved up. So with the chips are down,
I'm prepared. I've got my money. I've got my Bitcoin. I've got my gold buried in the backyard.
Right. That's I'm going to be fine because of that. Right. Or some relationship we have.
I've got the right friends. You know, I've got a power. I've got this ticket.
take a care of, got that take care of, you know, I've, where is it that you're looking
for you?
your salvation when that happens, right?
If it's some kind of instrumentality,
then that's idolatry.
Yeah.
Yeah, you know, something occurred to me
when we were talking about all this earlier,
which is that,
you know, this sense of trying to offer bribes
in order to get what you want.
I mean, it's, you know, when,
when Christ is in the wilderness
and the devil comes to tempt Him,
it's almost like the devil is trying to treat Christ
You know, I-
way. You know, like, I'll do this for you if you will only do this, you know, give, you know,
like he's trying to bribe him to get what it is that he wants. I mean, it's not that the analogy
doesn't completely hold, but I mean, but again, it's that theme of instrumentality and manipulation
and control, which is, you know, what the pagan gods demonstrate. It's what they expected.
and it's absolutely the opposite of what God demonstrates and what...
he expects and what he came and offered himself, right?
That destroys all the bribes,
that act of total selflessness and self giving.
So all right, well, to wrap up our conversation this evening,
the big thought that I had,
especially here towards the end,
is that so much in...
the modern world as we now experience it is designed to make us believe in magic.
It's ironic because supposedly we're modern enlightened rational people who don't believe
in magic.
But how much that we're being offered constantly is about if you do this thing, then you
will get these results, right?
And it's utterly addictive whether it's our...
health or our financial situation or our technology, you know, some kind of book that tells
you how to fix relationships or whatever it might be, right? We're being trained to engage
with the world in magical means, magical ways all the time. You know, that's not to say
that there is not a certain kind of instrumentality that is normal.
right? Like, you know, if I need to make myself breakfast, I pull out the ingredients and
I, you know, I make breakfast, right? I should expect the results. But at the same time,
as a Christian, I have to surround this stuff with prayer and with gratitude to God
for even giving me the ability to do those things, right? But again, it's so tough when we have
have so many buttons literally in
our lives, not to think of other people and even to think of God Himself as a kind of
button. If I just press this button, I should get this. If I just do this for this other
person, I should get that. But that's not the way that God shows us how to be. I was,
you know, on this past Sunday in our tradition, anyways, the gospel that we read was the gospel
of the keen and I woman who comes and approaches Christ when he's up in the region of Tyre
on this side and
and asks him to heal her daughter who's possessed by a demon of all things.
And she asks and she asks and the Lord Jesus initially ignores her and then eventually says things that could be taken as insulting towards her.
But she keeps going and she says, even when he says, you know, I was not, it's not right to give the food of the children, give it to dogs, you know, basically calling her a dog.
and
He persists and says, yes, but even the crumbs that fall from the master's table, the dogs,
you know, might ask for those, right?
So she approaches him with this humility.
She doesn't offer him a bribe.
She doesn't try to manipulate him.
She just makes this request and she accepts even what seems like insults from him.
accepts the bad treatment of his disciples, who tell him to send her away.
like she's bugging us, Lord, send her off, you know. And his response to her is,
great is your faith, great is your faith, you said to her, right? And this is what faith in
the Christian sense really is. This is what faithless in the Christian sense is, to
draw near to God and to ask for his mercy and to show gratitude and humility and to receive
whatever it is that you are
offers. Whatever it is he's going to give to realize that that's the thing that we actually
need for our salvation, right? Don't not to come in saying, look, this is what I expect
Lord and you know, you better do it. You know, I don't you know how much I did for you,
you know, that kind of thing, which again, that's magical thinking, that's manipulative thinking.
And so I think we need to be mindful in our modern period of how much we're being trained
to be minute.
And to have these kinds of instrumentalized expectations of God and of other people.
And you know, like Father Elijah called earlier and made mention of attention where we put our attention.
I think so many times we just can't be bothered. And so we don't put our attention where it really should be.
We'll pay attention to God long enough to get what we want. And then when we get what we want, you know, we look at something else.
Right.
Right. So I think a lot of the cure for this is
to reorient our attention towards what is highest, towards what is noblest, towards what is good and beautiful and holy.
And to practice gratitude for all that we receive and receive it as from the Lord because he has sent it to us for our salvation.
It's not easy. It's one of the great struggles of the modern age, but I think this is the way of salvation.
for those of us who live in this particular set of surroundings. Father Steven?
So one of the most difficult things, one of the most terrible in the original
sense things about our life in this world at this time is that we have a
future. We don't usually think about it that way but the future is a thing
that kind of...
always torments us, whether we want to admit it or not. In fact, a lot of people will say
that they're sort of tormented by their past.
But most of the times, when people are tormented by their past,
it's actually more that they're haunted by some
possible future that existed in the past, but now doesn't and can't.
We look toward the future and we see a lot of
of negative possible futures.
Thanks.
that we don't want to happen, that we don't want to transpire.
Roads that we don't want to travel and ways that we don't want to live.
And we want to ward those off.
And we can imagine futures where we want to live,
that we want to be true, that we want to come to fruition.
And we want to find ways to sort of guarantee those.
to make those permanent and secure in our minds.
And that's what draws us.
That's what drew ancient people to idolatry.
That's what draws us to various forms of idolatry.
We want to find the lever.
We want to find the button, the place where we can apply the pressure,
the procedure we could follow, the ritual we can do,
that will make sure that those good futures we want happen,
and those bad futures that we don't want don't.
so that we
We won't have to look back at our past anymore and see those possible good futures that died
and those negative futures that became our reality.
The problem is, they don't exist.
The problem is that we have a future because we're finite and we don't know what's going
to come in the next moment and the moment after that and the moments after that.
On the other hand, Christ has given us a hope, and I use the article there on purpose.
It is just that Christ has given us hope in a general sense, like the last thing out
of Pandora's jar, where, oh, things will get better.
Oh, tomorrow is another day, right?
Tomorrow may be a worst day.
Things may get worse and not better in any given person's life.
be honest.
but he's given us a hope, a particular hope.
And it's a particular hope because it's true.
It's not a possible future.
It is the future.
He's described it to us.
He's outlined it to us.
Christ is bringing it about in the world as we speak.
It will happen.
And rather than giving us a vote, right,
rather than us getting to choose.
what our part in that is going to be, what our lot in life is going to be, what we want,
our personal future to be.
Christ has given us that as a promise and told us that therefore we don't need to worry.
We don't need to spend our time worrying about what we will eat and what we will wear.
We don't need to spend our time worrying about those negative futures or imagining those
positive futures.
He has the future in his hand.
more than that.
He's told us how to participate in it.
He's told us how to do our peace in bringing that future about.
He's given us the tools to transform ourselves and our lives,
to transform our families, to form and transform our communities,
to transform our world ultimately,
which is what that future is going to ultimately mean.
And rather than trying to cast a vision for ourselves,
Make a mission statement.
and create some future that we find to our liking for whatever reason, usually based on our
base desires and passions. We could instead spend our time and our effort working toward
the future that is real. And when we do that, that's when we find the freedom from that
worry. That's where we find the freedom for worry about the future, the freedom for
being haunted by the past and what could have been, or we think should have been, or might
of Ben.
And that's where we come to day by day, regardless of our external circumstances, whether we're locked down in our houses,
whether we're getting a promotion at a job, whether we're paying off the mortgage on our house, whether we're losing our house, because we can't pay the mortgage,
that's where we experience the future that is in Christ.
The love and joy and peace of the Holy Spirit,
regardless of those circumstances.
So every one of us has something very concrete that we can do over and over again in every
moment of every day.
We can pray.
We can show love to the person who's sitting across from us or standing next to us or
near us.
We could just listen to them.
We could just smile at them.
We could just pay them a compliment.
We have all kinds of work to rebuild the alienation we were talking about.
about tonight to rebuild all of the broken relationships we were talking about tonight.
And as we do that, the future comes more and more into focus, becomes more and more real.
Because that's what St. Paul told us in Hebrews that our faithfulness to what God has called us to do
is the substance of the things that we hope for. It's what makes them substantial and real.
Well, thank you very much.
Father and that is our show for tonight.
Thank you everyone very much for listening.
If you didn't get a chance to call in
during the live broadcast,
we'd still up to hear from you either via email
at Lordofspirits at ancientfaith.com
or you can message us at the Lordofspirits podcast
Facebook page.
I read everything, Father Steven Schimms, some things,
but we can't respond to everything, that's for sure.
We do save some of what you send for possible use
and future episodes.
And join us for our live broadcast
on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month
at 7 PM East.
and 4PM Pacific except for next time when it will be Memorex.
That's true. If you're on Facebook, like our page,
join our discussion group, leave reviews and ratings everywhere,
but most importantly, share this show with a friend whom you know is going to love it.
And finally, be sure to go to asafethe.com,
stroke support, and that'll make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasts
stay on the air.
Thank you very much. Good night and make God bless you all.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener-supported presentation of Ancient Faith Radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000.
and thousands and thousands of thousands,
seeing with a loud voice worthy as the land
that was slain to receive power and riches
and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.
The saint of the day is the High Remarder Haralampus.
big ship of Naqnis.
This great saint was